<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Matt Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-04T13:45:28+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://lastexitcode.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Task Runner Explorer in Visual Studio for Mac]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2019/01/04/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/"/>
    <updated>2019-01-04T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2019/01/04/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-language-server-addin">Task Runner Explorer addin</a> provides a
Task Runner Explorer
window, similar to the one in Visual Studio on Windows, which can be used to run tasks with
Cake, Gulp, Grunt, NPM and TypeScript.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TaskRunnerExplorerWindowGruntNpmTasks.png" title="Task Runner Explorer window" alt="Task Runner Explorer Window"></p>

<h2>Features</h2>

<ul>
<li>Task Runner Explorer Window

<ul>
<li>View tasks</li>
<li>Run tasks</li>
<li>View task output</li>
<li>Run and cancel long running tasks, such as tcs watch</li>
<li>Configure tasks to run when specific IDE events occur

<ul>
<li>Before Build</li>
<li>After Build</li>
<li>Clean</li>
<li>Project Opened</li>
<li>Solution Opened</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Task Runners

<ul>
<li>Cake</li>
<li>Gulp</li>
<li>Grunt</li>
<li>NPM</li>
<li>TypeScript</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Supports</h2>

<ul>
<li>Visual Studio Mac 7.5 or later.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Task Runner Explorer</h2>

<p>To open the Task Runner Explorer window, from the View menu select Pads, then
select Task Runner Explorer.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/ViewTaskRunnerExplorerMenu.png" title="View Task Runner Explorer menu" alt="View Task Runner Explorer menu"></p>

<p>The Task Runner Explorer will look for files supported by a task runner in the
solution directory and the project directory. It will also look at all files
that have been added to a project or that have been added to a solution folder.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TaskRunnerExplorerTypeScriptNpmTasks.png" title="Task Runner Explorer TypeScript and NPM tasks" alt="Task Runner Explorer TypeScript and NPM tasks"></p>

<p>The top left of the Task Runner Explorer shows a list of projects
or the solution that have tasks available. This can be used to filter the tasks shown in the
Task Runner Explorer window.</p>

<p>Currently changes made to tasks will not be detected automatically. To refresh
the task information you can click the Refresh button
available at the top left of the Task Runner Explorer window.</p>

<h3>Running a Task</h3>

<p>To run a task you can double click it or right click and select Run.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TaskRunnerExplorerRunMenu.png" title="Task Runner Explorer Run menu" alt="Task Runner Explorer Run menu"></p>

<p>Output from the task is shown on the right hand side of the Task Runner Explorer
window.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TaskRunnerNpmUpdateRunning.png" title="NPM update running" alt="NPM update running"></p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/NpmUpdateRunCompleted.png" title="NPM update completed" alt="NPM update completed"></p>

<p>A long running task, such as tcs watch, will run until the solution is closed,
or the Stop button, available on the right hand side
of the Task Runner Explorer window, is clicked.</p>

<h3>Binding Tasks to IDE Events</h3>

<p>Tasks can be configured to run when the following IDE events occur:</p>

<ul>
<li>After Build</li>
<li>Before Build</li>
<li>Clean</li>
<li>Project or Solution Opened</li>
</ul>


<p>If the task runner file is in a project directory then the build and clean
events are associated with the project. If the task runner file is in a solution directory
then the build events are associated with the solution.</p>

<p>To configure a task, right click it, select Bindings and then select the
event.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TaskRunnerExplorerBindingsMenu.png" title="Task Runner Explorer Bindings menu" alt="Task Runner Explorer Bindings menu"></p>

<p>The binding will be displayed in the Bindings tab and will also be shown as
checked when the context menu for the task is opened.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TaskRunnerExplorerBeforeBuildBindingAdded.png" title="Task Runner Explorer Before Build binding added" alt="Task Runner Explorer Before Build binding added"></p>

<p>To remove the binding you can right click the task, select Bindings and
select the event again to uncheck it. Alternatively you can right click
it in the Bindings tab and select Remove.</p>

<p>The order in which the tasks are run for a particular IDE event can be changed
by right clicking the binding in the Bindings tab and selecting Move Up or Move Down.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TaskRunnerExplorerBindingsMoveDownMenu.png" title="Task Runner Explorer binding Move Up and Down menus" alt="Task Runner Explorer binding Move Up and Down menus"></p>

<p>The binding information is typically saved in a file in the same directory as the corresponding task
runner file, however this depends on how the task runner is implemented.</p>

<h3>Disabling Automatic Running of Tasks</h3>

<p>In preferences there is a Task Runner Explorer section which shows
a check box that can be used to enable or disable the automatic
running of tasks on opening a project or solution, and when building or cleaning.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TaskRunnerPreferences.png" title="Preferences - Automatically run tasks option" alt="Preferences - Automatically run tasks option"></p>

<h2>Cake Task Runner</h2>

<p>The Cake task runner supports running tasks defined in a build.cake file.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/CakeTaskRunner.png" title="Cake Task Runner" alt="Cake Task Runner"></p>

<p>This is based on the <a href="https://github.com/cake-build/cake-vs">Cake Task Runner for Visual Studio</a>.</p>

<h2>Gulp Task Runner</h2>

<p>The Gulp task runner supports running tasks defined in a gulpfile.js file.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/GulpTaskRunner.png" title="Gulp Task Runner" alt="Gulp Task Runner"></p>

<p><a href="https://gulpjs.com">Gulp</a> needs to be installed separately.</p>

<h2>Grunt Task Runner</h2>

<p>The Grunt task runner supports running tasks defined in a Gruntfile.js file.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/GruntTaskRunner.png" title="Grunt Task Runner" alt="Grunt Task Runner"></p>

<p><a href="https://gruntjs.com">Grunt</a> needs to be installed separately.</p>

<h2>NPM Task Runner</h2>

<p>The NPM task runner supports running tasks defined in a package.json file.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/NpmTaskRunner.png" title="NPM task runner" alt="NPM task runner"></p>

<p>The NPM task runner is a port of <a href="https://madskristensen.net/">Mads Kristensen&rsquo;s</a>
<a href="https://github.com/madskristensen/NpmTaskRunner">NPM Task Runner</a>.</p>

<p>The NPM task runner supports running with the verbose NPM option defined. If a
task is selected then a button will be displayed on the left hand side of the
Task Runner Explorer window. If this is selected then npm will be passed the
<code>-d</code> argument when it is run.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/NpmTaskRunnerVerboseButton.png" title="NPM task runner Verbose button" alt="NPM task runner Verbose button"></p>

<p>NPM needs to be installed separately.</p>

<h2>TypeScript Task Runner</h2>

<p>The TypeScript task runner supports running tcs build and tcs watch if a tsconfig.json file
is found.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TypeScriptTaskRunner.png" title="TypeScript task runner" alt="TypeScript task runner"></p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TaskRunnerExplorerInVisualStudioMac/TypeScriptWatchTaskOutput.png" title="TypeScript tcs watch output" alt="TypeScript tcs watch output"></p>

<p>The TypeScript task runner will try to use tsc that is distributed with the Web Tools extension that
is included in Visual Studio for Mac. If the Web Tools extension is not installed then the task
runner will fall back to running tsc directly.</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>There are two addins to be installed:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-task-runner-addin/releases/download/0.1/MonoDevelop.TaskRunner_0.1.mpack">Task Runner</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-task-runner-addin/releases/download/0.1/MonoDevelop.TaskRunnersBundle_0.1.mpack">Task Runners Bundle</a></li>
</ul>


<p>The Task Runner is the main addin. This will be used by other task runner addins and provides the
main task runner API and services.</p>

<p>The Task Runners Bundle addin contains the Cake, Gulp, Grunt, NPM and TypeScript task runners. These
are currently included together as a single addin instead of being distributed separately.</p>

<p>Download both of the above .mpack files. Install the Task Runner addin first since the Task Runners Bundle
addin depends on it. To install an addin&rsquo;s .mpack file, open the Extensions Manager
by selecting Extensions&hellip; from the main menu. Click the Install from file button. Select the .mpack file
and then click the Open button. After installing both the addins restart Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<p>These addins are not currently available from the main Visual Studio for Mac extensions server.</p>

<h2>Source Code</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-language-server-addin">Task Runner Explorer for Visual Studio for Mac</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-cake-task-runner">Cake Task Runner for Visual Studio for Mac</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-grunt-task-runner">Grunt Task Runner for Visual Studio for Mac</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-gulp-task-runner">Gulp Task Runner for Visual Studio for Mac</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/NpmTaskRunner">NPM Task Runner for Visual Studio for Mac</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-typescript-task-runner">TypeScript Task Runner for Visual Studio for Mac</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NuGet Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.7]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/12/19/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-7/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-19T14:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/12/19/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> NuGet 4.8 support</li>
<li> Support PackageReferences without a Version</li>
<li> Fixed NuGet sdk resolver not being found in Mono 5.16</li>
<li> Fixed null reference exception in package compatiblity check</li>
<li> Fixed Update menu enabled when project has no PackageReferences</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.7</a>
can be found in the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#whats-new-in-77">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>NuGet 4.8 support</h2>

<p><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/release-notes/nuget-4.8-rtm">NuGet 4.8.0.5385</a> is now
included with Visual Studio for Mac 7.7.2.</p>

<h2>Support PackageReferences without a Version</h2>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac did not support projects that used PackageReferences without
specifying a version.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ItemGroup&gt;
    &lt;PackageReference Include="Newtonsoft.Json" /&gt;
&lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The version may be defined elsewhere in another MSBuild file, such as the Directory.props file,
or by the .NET Core SDK, as with the
Microsoft.AspNetCore.App PackageReference in ASP.NET Core projects. By default a
PackageReference without a version will restore the lowest available version for
the NuGet package.</p>

<p>However in Visual Studio for Mac there were several problems with PackageReferences that
did not specify a version.</p>

<p>Opening a project with a PackageReference without a Version
would result in an ArgumentNullException being logged and the
Add Packages dialog could not be opened.</p>

<p>If the PackageReference, in a non-SDK project, had no Version
then it was not displayed in the Packages folder and a null reference
exception was logged. The Solution window would try to find
the package to check if it was installed which is not possible
with a missing version and NuGet&rsquo;s VersionFolderPathResolver
would throw a null reference exception.</p>

<p>If a PackageReference had no Version then a null reference exception
was logged when checking for updates. A null version is now handled.</p>

<p>Right clicking the package in the Packages folder would log a
null reference exception if a non-SDK style project was used and it
had a PackageReference without a version. This is now handled and the
menu label will show &ldquo;Version None&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Fixed NuGet sdk resolver not being found in Mono 5.16</strong></p>

<p>More recent versions of MSBuild, such as MSBuild 16.0.40 which is included
with Mono 5.16.0.173, allow the sdk resolver to use a manifest.xml file to
define the assembly where the resolver can be found:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;SdkResolver&gt;
  &lt;Path&gt;..\..\Microsoft.Build.NuGetSdkResolver.dll&lt;/Path&gt;
&lt;/SdkResolver&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This manifest file not supported and resulted in the NuGet sdk resolver not
being loaded. Any projects that use an MSBuild sdk from a NuGet
package no longer worked and would result in an &lsquo;Invalid configuration
mapping&rsquo; error shown in the Solution window. The sdk resolution in
Visual Studio for Mac has now
been updated based on the latest MSBuild source code.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed null reference exception in compatiblity check</strong></p>

<p>Changing the target framework of a project that uses a packages.config
file will result in a package compatiblity check being run.
If the project had both a PackageReference and a packages.config file
the package compatiblity check would fail with a null
reference exception. Visual Studio for Mac was treating the project as
though it was using a packages.config file, when it should have been
treated as a PackageReference project. This resulted in a null
reference exception being thrown when checking for package compatiblity.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed Update menu enabled when project has no PackageReferences</strong></p>

<p>The Update menu was enabled if the project used PackageReferences but
had none in the project. Without any PackageReferences in the
project there is no packages to update. The check to determine if the Update
menu should be enabled has been changed to make sure the project has
PackageReferences in the project file, not just imported
PackageReferences. The Update
NuGet Packages menu, which is used to update packages for the solution,
has also been changed to have the same behaviour.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Proxy Testing a Mac Application with Apache]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/10/28/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithApache/"/>
    <updated>2018-10-28T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/10/28/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithApache</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here we look at using <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/">Apache</a> as
a proxy server in order to test that a Mac client application, such as Safari or Visual Studio for Mac, can make web
requests through a proxy. Enabling Basic and NTLM proxy authentication with Apache will be covered, as well as using
the Apache as a proxy without any authentication.</p>

<p>Apache will run on a separate Windows machine. Using a separate machine
allows us to check that the Mac client application is not bypassing the proxy and making direct
web requests to any server. This check can be done by configuring the local firewall to block all direct
connections out from the Mac machine but allow connections from the machine running Apache.</p>

<ul>
<li>Mac High Sierra 10.13</li>
<li><a href="https://www.apachehaus.com/cgi-bin/download.plx">Apache 2.4.35 on Windows</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Apache Proxy &ndash; No authentication</h2>

<p>Unzip Apache and extract the files to c:\Apache24\ which is the default ServerRoot configured in the conf\httpd.conf
file.</p>

<pre><code>Define SRVROOT "/Apache24"
</code></pre>

<p>In the httpd.config file configure the port to be used by the Apache server if required.
By default port 80 is used. Here we will be using port 8888.</p>

<pre><code>Listen 8888
ServerName localhost:8888
</code></pre>

<p><a href="https://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/mod_proxy.html">mod_proxy</a>,
<a href="https://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/mod_proxy_connect.html">mod_proxy_connect</a> and
<a href="https://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/mod_proxy_http.html">mod_proxy_http</a> should be loaded.
Edit the http.conf file and ensure these modules are loaded.</p>

<pre><code>LoadModule proxy_module modules/mod_proxy.so
LoadModule proxy_connect_module modules/mod_proxy_connect.so
LoadModule proxy_http_module modules/mod_proxy_http.so
</code></pre>

<p>Add a VirtualHost and Proxy section to the httpd.conf file.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;VirtualHost *&gt;
     ProxyRequests On

    &lt;Proxy *&gt;
        Require all granted
    &lt;/Proxy&gt;
&lt;/VirtualHost&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>To run Apache, open a command prompt, change into the Apache24\bin directory, then run httpd.exe</p>

<pre><code>cd c:\Apache24\bin
httpd.exe
</code></pre>

<p>On running Apache for the first time you will see a Windows Firewall dialog.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithApache/FirewallAlertApache.png" title="Windows Firewall alert for Apache" alt="Windows Firewall alert for Apache"></p>

<p>Allow Apache to access both the private and public networks.</p>

<p>Configuring the Mac to use Apache as its proxy server can be done by opening System Preferences &ndash; Network.
For the active network select the Advanced button and open the Proxies tab. Enter the machine IP address
where Apache is running and its port into the Web Proxy (HTTP) and Secure Web Proxy (HTTPS) sections, and ensure both
of these are checked.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithApache/MacNetworkWebProxySettings.png" title="Mac web proxy settings" alt="Mac web proxy settings"></p>

<p>Finally click OK and Apply to enable the proxy settings.</p>

<p>Now http and https requests should be sent through Apache. A simple way to test this is
to open Safari and view a web page. In the C:\Apache24\logs\access.log file you should see entries for the
sites accessed.</p>

<pre><code>192.168.1.100 - - [28/Oct/2018:12:18:47 +0000] "GET http://neverssl.com/ HTTP/1.1" 200 1183
192.168.1.100 - - [28/Oct/2018:12:18:47 +0000] "GET http://neverssl.com/favicon.ico HTTP/1.1" 200 124
192.168.1.100 - - [28/Oct/2018:12:18:41 +0000] "CONNECT www.nuget.org:443 HTTP/1.1" 200 -
</code></pre>

<h2>Apache Proxy &ndash; Basic authentication</h2>

<p>To enable Basic authentication change the Proxy section in the httpd.conf file as shown below.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;VirtualHost *&gt;
     ProxyRequests On

    &lt;Proxy *&gt;
        AuthType Basic
        AuthName "Authentication required"
        AuthBasicProvider file
        AuthUserFile proxy-password.file
        Require valid-user
    &lt;/Proxy&gt;
&lt;/VirtualHost&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Here we will be using <a href="https://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/programs/htpasswd.html">htpasswd.exe</a> to create a file to
store the username and password required to authenticate against
the proxy server. htpasswd.exe is in the Apache bin directory. Run the following to generate the proxy-password.file,
replacing user with the username to be used with the proxy.</p>

<pre><code>htpasswd.exe -c proxy-password.file user
</code></pre>

<p>Enter the password when prompted.</p>

<p>Copy the proxy-password.file to the Apache server&rsquo;s root directory c:\Apache24</p>

<p>To make it easier to see the basic auth header being sent you may want to enable
<a href="https://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/mod_log_forensic.html">forensic logging</a> in Apache.
To do this add a LoadModule to the httpd.conf file.</p>

<pre><code>LoadModule log_forensic_module modules/mod_log_forensic.so
</code></pre>

<p>Define the path to the forensic log file using an IfModule.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;IfModule log_forensic_module&gt; 
    ForensicLog "logs/forensic.log"
&lt;/IfModule&gt; 
</code></pre>

<p>Run httpd.exe from the Apache24\bin directory.</p>

<p>When connecting through the proxy
for the first time the Mac will show a dialog asking for credentials.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithApache/ProxyAuthenticationRequiredDialog.png" title="Mac proxy authentication required dialog" alt="Mac proxy authentication required dialog"></p>

<p>Clicking the System Preferences button will show open a dialog where you can enter the credentials for the proxy.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithApache/ProxyCredentialsDialog.png" title="Mac proxy authentcation required - credentials dialog" alt="Mac proxy authentication required - credentials dialog"></p>

<p>Entering the credentials will result in the Mac&rsquo;s key chain being updated with the credentials associated with the proxy&rsquo;s address.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithApache/ProxyCredentialsMacKeyChain.png" title="Proxy credentials stored in Mac key chain" alt="Proxy credentials stored in Mac key chain"></p>

<p>If you open the Mac&rsquo;s Network settings you will see the Web Proxy and Secure Web Proxy settings now have a username and password
associated with them.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithApache/MacNetworkSettingsProxyUserNamePassword.png" title="Username and password associated with proxy in network settings" alt="Username and password associated with proxy in network settings"></p>

<p>In the Apache access.log you should see the requests being made and a Proxy authentication 407 status code.</p>

<pre><code>192.168.1.100 - - [28/Oct/2018:12:44:47 +0000] "CONNECT www.nuget.org:443 HTTP/1.1" 407 415
192.168.1.100 - - [28/Oct/2018:12:44:53 +0000] "GET http://neverssl.com/ HTTP/1.1" 407 415
</code></pre>

<p>In the forensic.log file you should see the basic proxy authorization header being used by the Mac.</p>

<pre><code>GET http%3a//neverssl.com/ HTTP/1.1|Host:neverssl.com|Connection:keep-alive|Proxy-Connection:keep-alive|Upgrade-Insecure-Requests:1|Proxy-Authorization:Basic MTox|Accept:text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8|User-Agent:Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10_13_6) AppleWebKit/605.1.15 (KHTML, like Gecko) Version/12.0 Safari/605.1.15|Accept-Language:en-gb|DNT:1|Accept-Encoding:gzip, deflate
CONNECT www.nuget.org%3a443 HTTP/1.1|Host:www.nuget.org%3a443|User-Agent:Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10_13_6) AppleWebKit/605.1.15 (KHTML, like Gecko) Version/12.0 Safari/605.1.15|Connection:keep-alive|Proxy-Authorization:Basic MTox|Proxy-Connection:keep-alive
</code></pre>

<h2>Apache Proxy &ndash; NTLM authentication</h2>

<p>In order to enable NTLM authentication the <a href="https://github.com/TQsoft-GmbH/mod_authn_ntlm">NTLM authentication module</a> needs to be downloaded.
Download <a href="https://www.apachehaus.com/cgi-bin/download.plx">Mod Auth NTLM for Apache 2.4.x x64 &ndash; mod_authn_ntml.zip</a>,
extract the files and copy the mod_auth_ntlm.so file to the Apache24\modules directory.</p>

<p>Add a LoadModule to the httpd.conf file for the mod_authn_ntlm.so file.</p>

<pre><code>LoadModule auth_ntlm_module modules/mod_authn_ntlm.so
</code></pre>

<p>Change the VirtualHost Proxy section as shown below:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;VirtualHost *&gt;
    ProxyRequests On

    &lt;Proxy *&gt;
        AuthType SSPI
        AuthName "Auth required"
        NTLMAuth On
        NTLMAuthoritative On

        &lt;RequireAll&gt;
            &lt;RequireAny&gt;
                Require valid-user
            &lt;/RequireAny&gt;

            &lt;RequireNone&gt;
                Require user "ANONYMOUS LOGON"
                Require user "NT AUTHORITY\ANONYMOUS LOGON"
            &lt;/RequireNone&gt;
        &lt;/RequireAll&gt;
    &lt;/Proxy&gt;
&lt;/VirtualHost&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The username and password used to authenticate against the proxy needs to match an account on the Windows machine.
As with basic authentication, the Mac will prompt for credentials if they do not match
what is stored in the key chain for the proxy.</p>

<p>Run httpd.exe and then use Safari to open a web site to check web requests are being sent through the proxy.
You should see the Windows account being used to authenticate in Apache&rsquo;s access.log.</p>

<pre><code>192.168.1.100 - - [28/Oct/2018:13:09:19 +0000] "GET http://neverssl.com/ HTTP/1.1" 407 415
192.168.1.100 - windows\\useraccount [28/Oct/2018:13:09:19 +0000] "GET http://neverssl.com/ HTTP/1.1" 304 -
192.168.1.100 - - [28/Oct/2018:13:09:38 +0000] "CONNECT www.nuget.org:443 HTTP/1.1" 407 415
192.168.1.100 - windows\\useraccount [28/Oct/2018:13:09:12 +0000] "CONNECT www.nuget.org:443 HTTP/1.1" 200 -
</code></pre>

<p>The forensic log should show that the NTLM header is being used by the Mac.</p>

<pre><code>CONNECT www.nuget.org%3a443 HTTP/1.1|Host:www.nuget.org%3a443|User-Agent:Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10_13_6) AppleWebKit/605.1.15 (KHTML, like Gecko) Version/12.0 Safari/605.1.15|Connection:keep-alive|Proxy-Authorization:NTLM T...|Proxy-Connection:keep-alive
GET http%3a//neverssl.com/ HTTP/1.1|Host:neverssl.com|Proxy-Connection:keep-alive|Proxy-Authorization:NTLM T...|If-Modified-Since:Thu, 14 Jun 2018 00%3a16%3a40 GMT|Accept:text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8|Accept-Language:en-gb|Accept-Encoding:gzip, deflate|Content-Length:0|User-Agent:Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10_13_6) AppleWebKit/605.1.15 (KHTML, like Gecko) Version/12.0 Safari/605.1.15|Connection:keep-alive|Upgrade-Insecure-Requests:1|DNT:1
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Proxy Testing a Mac Application with Fiddler]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/10/21/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/"/>
    <updated>2018-10-21T12:38:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/10/21/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here we look at using <a href="https://www.telerik.com/fiddler">Fiddler</a> as
a proxy server in order to test a Mac client application, such as Safari or Visual Studio for Mac, can make web
requests through the proxy. Enabling Basic proxy authentication with Fiddler will be covered, as well as using
the Fiddler as a proxy without any authentication.</p>

<p>Fiddler will run on a separate Windows machine. Using a separate machine
allows us to check that the Mac client application is not bypassing the proxy and making direct
web requests to any server. This check can be done by configuring the local firewall to block all direct
connections out from the Mac machine but allow connections from the machine running Fiddler.</p>

<ul>
<li>Mac High Sierra 10.13</li>
<li>Fiddler 5.0 on Windows</li>
</ul>


<h2>Fiddler Proxy &ndash; No authentication</h2>

<p>To enable the Mac to use Fiddler as its proxy first configure Fiddler to allow remote connections.
This can be done by open the Tools menu, selecting Options, opening the Connections tab, and
checking <a href="http://docs.telerik.com/fiddler/Configure-Fiddler/Tasks/MonitorRemoteMachine">Allow remote computers to connect</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/FiddlerRemoteConnections.png" title="Fiddler allow remote connections" alt="Fiddler allow remote connections"></p>

<p>Configuring the Mac to use Fiddler as its proxy server can be done by opening System Preferences &ndash; Network.
For the active network select the Advanced button and open the Proxies tab. Enter the Fiddler&rsquo;s machine IP address and
port into the Web Proxy (HTTP) and Secure Web Proxy (HTTPS) sections, and ensure both
of these are checked.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/MacNetworkWebProxySettings.png" title="Mac web proxy settings" alt="Mac web proxy settings"></p>

<p>Finally click OK and Apply to enable the proxy settings.</p>

<p>Now http and https requests should be sent through Fiddler. A simple way to test this is
to open Safari and open a web page.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/FiddlerNuGetHttpsRequest.png" title="Fiddler https request recorded" alt="Fiddler https request recorded"></p>

<h2>Fiddler Proxy &ndash; Basic authentication</h2>

<p>To enable Basic proxy authentication in Fiddler open the Rules menu and ensure that
Require Proxy Authentication is checked.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/FiddlerProxyAuthEnabled.png" title="Fiddler require proxy authentication option" alt="Fiddler require proxy authentication option"></p>

<p>This will result in Fiddler requiring Basic authentication with a username &lsquo;1&rsquo; and a
password &lsquo;1&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Unfortunately it seems that the native Mac networking API does not work with Fiddler
for https requests but will work for non-secure http requests. Opening a web page in Safari will cause the Mac to prompt for
the proxy credentials.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/ProxyAuthenticationRequiredDialog.png" title="Mac proxy authentication required dialog" alt="Mac proxy authentication required dialog"></p>

<p>Clicking the System Preferences button will show open a dialog where you can enter the credentials for the proxy.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/ProxyCredentialsDialog.png" title="Mac proxy authentcation required - credentials dialog" alt="Mac proxy authentication required - credentials dialog"></p>

<p>Entering the credentials will result in the Mac&rsquo;s key chain being updated with the credentials associated with the proxy&rsquo;s address.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/ProxyCredentialsMacKeyChain.png" title="Proxy credentials stored in Mac key chain" alt="Proxy credentials stored in Mac key chain"></p>

<p>If you open the Mac&rsquo;s Network settings you will see the Web Proxy and Secure Web Proxy settings now have a username and password
associated with them.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/MacNetworkSettingsProxyUserNamePassword.png" title="Username and password associated with proxy in network settings" alt="Username and password associated with proxy in network settings"></p>

<p>Safari will display an error page when accessing a web page over https when the Mac is configured to use Fiddler&rsquo;s basic authentation proxy.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/SafariProxyServerError.png" title="Safari 310 proxy error" alt="Safari 310 proxy error"></p>

<p>It seems that for a https request the Mac sends the request with two keep alive headers:</p>

<ul>
<li>Connection: keep-alive</li>
<li>Proxy-Connection: keep-alive</li>
</ul>


<p>Fiddler responds with a 407 proxy authentication required response and a close
header.</p>

<ul>
<li>Connection: close</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ProxyTestingMacApplicationWithFiddler/FiddlerProxyAuthHttpsRequestDenied.png" title="Fiddler https request denied" alt="Fiddler https request denied"></p>

<p>Since the keep-alive is not being honoured by Fiddler the web request sent from the Mac fails and an kCFErrorDomainCFNetwork 310
error occurs. This maps to the kCFErrorHTTPSProxyConnectionFailure status code.</p>

<p>Other applications that do not use the native Mac networking API, such as the Google Chrome web browser,
will work with Fiddler and will prompt for credentials.</p>

<p>Unfortunately you currently cannot use Fiddler with basic proxy authentication enabled to test
a Mac application making https requests. As an alternative you can use another proxy server, such as Apache.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.NET Core Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.6]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/09/02/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-6/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-02T11:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/09/02/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li>NuGet SDK resolver now used to find NuGet SDK packages</li>
<li>Fixed Synchronous operation cancelled message on stopping debugging</li>
<li>Fixed debugger hanging when debugging unit tests</li>
<li>Fixed command line arguments not used with a new project</li>
<li>Fixed hang when discovering unit tests</li>
<li>Allow loading of SDK style projects without a main PropertyGroup</li>
<li>Fixed TargetFramework not being updated in project</li>
<li>Fixed .xaml.cs code completion in new Xamarin.Forms .NET Standard project</li>
<li>Fixed default build action for new HTML file</li>
<li>Fixed SDK version not being parsed from Sdk attribute</li>
<li>Fixed null reference on opening .NET Core project with sdk version</li>
<li>Fixed editor errors when .NET Standard assembly referenced in Xamarin.iOS project</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.6</a>
can be found in the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#whats-new-in-76">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>NuGet SDK resolver now used to find NuGet SDK packages</h2>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac now has support for the
<a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/msbuild/issues/2803">NuGet SDK resolver</a>. The NuGet
SDK resolver will download and install SDKs for SDK style
projects if these SDKs are missing.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Project Sdk="My.Custom.Sdk/2.3.4"&gt;
  ...
&lt;/Project&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The SDK resolution is done in the background
when the project is opened and there is currently no visual indication that
this is happening.</p>

<p>The NuGet library assemblies are not available to the remote MSBuild host used by
Visual Studio for Mac so the NuGet SDK resolver was previously failing to load. The NuGet SDK
resolver supports a MSBUILD_NUGET_PATH environment variable which is now set by
Visual Studio for Mac to point to the directory containing the NuGet assemblies
that are included with the IDE.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Fixed synchronous operation cancelled message on stopping debugging</strong></p>

<p>Stopping the .NET Core debugger would sometimes result in
a dialog being displayed indicating that the debugger operation failed.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-6/DebuggerOperationFailedMessage.png" title="Debugger operation failed - Synchronous operation cancelled - dialog" alt="Debugger operation failed - Synchronous operation cancelled - dialog"></p>

<p><strong>Fixed debugger hanging when debugging unit tests</strong></p>

<p>The .NET Core debugger would sometimes hang Visual Studio for Mac when debugging unit tests.
The problem was that if the breakpoint was placed on an invalid line then the .NET Core debugger
would send back the adjusted breakpoint location. Visual Studio for Mac would then send back
an incorrect breakpoint line back to the .NET Core debugger, which again resulted in the debugger
sending back a corrected line. This would repeat resulting in the IDE and debugger
getting stuck in a loop.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed command line arguments not used with a new project</strong></p>

<p>Creating a new .NET Core console project, editing the project run
configuration to use extra command line arguments, or to not use the
external console, then building and running the project would result
in the project run configuration not being used. No extra
arguments would be passed to the console project, and the external
console would still be used. This could be fixed by closing and
re-opening the solution.</p>

<p>The problem was that when the project is re-evaluated, after it is
created, its run configurations are cleared. The solution&rsquo;s
startup run configuration would still be using
the original project run configuration that was no longer used.
Changes made to the project run configuration then had no affect. Closing and
re-opening the solution fixed this since
the run configuration defined in the .csproj.user file is re-used when the
project is re-evaluated on reloading so both the solution run configuration and
the project run configuration refer to the same configuration. To fix this,
on re-evaluating the project, if the solution&rsquo;s run configuration
refers to a project run configuration that has been removed then
the solution&rsquo;s startup configuration is refreshed.</p>

<p>Note that there is a similar problem with multiple solution run
configurations that can occur which is not addressed by this fix.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed hang when discovering unit tests</strong></p>

<p>Opening a solution containing a .NET Core test project would sometimes
result in the IDE hanging when discovering tests. On running <code>kill -QUIT pid</code>
the IDE log would show a background thread and the UI thread both
awaiting test discovery to complete:</p>

<pre><code>var discoveredTests = await VsTestDiscoveryAdapter.Instance.DiscoverTestsAsync (Project);

VsTestProjectTestSuite/&lt;OnCreateTests&gt;d__12.MoveNext
in MonoDevelop.UnitTesting.VsTest/VsTestProjectTestSuite.cs:95
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Allow loading of SDK style projects without a main PropertyGroup</strong></p>

<p>On loading an SDK style project that did not have a main PropertyGroup
Visual Studio for Mac would show the error message
&ldquo;Error while trying to load project:
Object reference not set to an instance of an object&rdquo;.</p>

<p>A project may define MSBuild properties in a Directory.Build.props file
instead of having this in the main project file. It is then
possible for the main project file to have no main property group.</p>

<p>Directory.Build.props:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Project&gt;
  &lt;PropertyGroup&gt;
    &lt;OutputType&gt;Exe&lt;/OutputType&gt;
    &lt;TargetFramework&gt;netcoreapp2.1&lt;/TargetFramework&gt;
  &lt;/PropertyGroup&gt;
&lt;/Project&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>MainProject.csproj:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Project Sdk="Microsoft.NET.Sdk"&gt;
&lt;/Project&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac now handles the missing main PropertyGroup.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed TargetFramework not being updated in project</strong></p>

<p>Changing a .NET Core project&rsquo;s target framework to a different version in
Project Options, then re-opening Project Options and changing the
target framework version back again, would result in the target framework
not being updated in the project. The problem was the original target framework the
project had on opening was cached and the changing back to the same
target framework version was being ignored resulting in the project file not
being updated.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed .xaml.cs code completion in new Xamarin.Forms .NET Standard project</strong></p>

<p>Creating a new Xamarin.Forms .NET Standard project, then
modifing the .xaml to add new named UI items, would result in no
code completion in the .xaml.cs file for these new items
until the solution was closed and re-opened. The problem was that the
.xaml and .xaml.cs files
were being removed from the file information held in memory
when the project was re-evaluated. On re-evaluation, after
the NuGet restore is first run for the project, the old MSBuild items for the
.xaml and .xaml.cs file have the wrong metadata, so they need
to be removed, whilst new MSBuild items with the updated metadata
need to be added. The removal was done after adding the updated files
and, since they had the same filename, the new updated files were being
removed. The removal is now done before adding the updated files to
avoid the files being removed incorrectly.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed default build action for new HTML file</strong></p>

<p>Adding a new .html file to the wwwroot folder of an ASP.NET Core
project would add the file as a None item instead of a Content
item. This would result in the .html file not being used when
publishing the project. When &lsquo;dotnet publish&rsquo; was used the
publish directory would not contain the .html file.</p>

<p>ASP.NET Core projects have different build actions for files based on where they
are added. A .html file in the root directory would be a None item by default,
whilst a .html file in the wwwroot directory would be a Content item
by default. To fix this the default build action for a file is
determined by the file wildcard information available from the .NET
Core SDK.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed SDK version not being parsed from Sdk attribute</strong></p>

<p>The Sdk attribute would have its forward slash / replaced with a
backslash \ which meant Visual Studio for Mac was creating an
SdkReference with the wrong name, for example:</p>

<pre><code>Microsoft.NET.Sdk.Razor\2.1.0-preview2-final
</code></pre>

<p>Instead of having Microsoft.NET.Sdk.Razor as the name with the
version being separate.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed null reference on opening .NET Core project with SDK version</strong></p>

<p>Opening a SDK style project that used a Sdk attribute with a version
would show an error message &ldquo;Error while trying to load project:
Object reference not set to an instance of an object&rdquo;. The problem
was that an SdkResolver can return null from its Resolve method.
These null results were added to a list and then an attempt was made
to log the result warnings on a null result.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Project Sdk="Microsoft.NET.Sdk.Razor/2.1.0-preview2-final"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Fixed editor errors when .NET Standard assembly referenced in Xamarin.iOS project</strong></p>

<p>When a Xamarin.iOS project used an assembly that was compiled
for .NET Standard, such as the assembly in the
System.Collections.Immutable NuGet package, the netstandard assembly
was not made available for code completion. This then resulted in the text editor
showing errors even though the project could be compiled succesfully.
The errors displayed were similar to:</p>

<pre><code>  The type 'ValueType' is defined in an assembly that is not
  referenced. You must add a reference to assembly 'netstandard,
  Version=2.0.0.0, Culture=neutral, PublicKeytoken=cc7b1dffcd2ddd51'.
</code></pre>

<p>Now a check is made to determine
if an assembly is referencing netstandard and if so the facade assemblies,
which for Xamarin.iOS will include the netstandard.dll, are made available
for code completion. Previously only a check was made for the project having
an assembly referencing System.Runtime before including the facade assemblies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NuGet Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.6]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/09/01/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-6/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-01T14:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/09/01/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> Support no-op package restore on opening a solution</li>
<li> Added basic support for the NuGet SDK resolver</li>
<li> Fixed source code transformations not available in code completion</li>
<li> Fixed incorrect FSharp.Core NuGet package being restored</li>
<li> Fixed updating PackageReference removing metadata</li>
<li> Fixed build error after updating Xamarin.Forms PackageReference</li>
<li> Fixed build error after updating Xamarin.Forms NuGet package</li>
<li> Fixed editor errors when .NET Standard assembly referenced in Xamarin.iOS project</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.6</a>
can be found in the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#whats-new-in-76">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>Support no-op package restore on opening a solution</h2>

<p>On opening a solution a NuGet package restore was always run for projects that use
PackageReferences. This resulted in the project.assets.json file being
re-generated and the projects being re-evaluated. Now if the package
references have not changed a no-op restore will occur. This makes the
restore faster on opening a solution. It also prevents Visual Studio for Mac
going online to fetch NuGet package information if a wildcard is used for
a PackageReference or if the package version cannot be found. In the Package
Console when a no-op restore occurs you will see the following
messages:</p>

<pre><code>Assets file has not changed. Skipping assets file writing.
No-Op restore. The cache will not be updated.
</code></pre>

<h2>Allow NuGet SDK resolver to find NuGet SDK packages</h2>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac now has basic support for the
<a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/msbuild/issues/2803">NuGet SDK resolver</a>. The NuGet
SDK resolver will download and install SDKs for SDK style
projects if these SDKs are missing.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Project Sdk="My.Custom.Sdk/2.3.4"&gt;
  ...
&lt;/Project&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The SDK resolution is done in the background
when the project is opened and there is currently no visual indication that
this is happening.</p>

<p>The NuGet library assemblies are not available to the remote MSBuild host used by
Visual Studio for Mac so the NuGet SDK resolver was previously failing to load. The NuGet SDK
resolver supports a MSBUILD_NUGET_PATH environment variable which is now set by
Visual Studio for Mac to point to the directory containing the NuGet assemblies
that are included with the IDE.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Source code transformations not available in code completion</strong></p>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac now ensures that files generated by a NuGet
package are available for code completion. One example
NuGet package that generates files is the
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/LibLog/">LibLog NuGet package</a>.</p>

<p>The LibLog NuGet package has contentFiles that are processed by
MSBuild and converted into .cs files. These .cs files are implicitly included
in the project. These files are generated in the obj folder. For example:</p>

<pre><code>obj/Debug/netstandard2.0/NuGet/SomeID/LibLog/5.0.0/ILog.cs
</code></pre>

<p>The types defined inside these generated files can be referenced by
code in the project. Whilst the project would compile without any errors
the text editor would show errors about the
types from the generated files being undefined.</p>

<p>These generated files are not created or returned by running the
CoreCompileDependsOn MSBuild target, which is currently used to find generated
files. Now when the CoreCompileDependsOn target is evaluated, Visual Studio for
Mac will also run NuGet specific
MSBuild targets to ensure any NuGet package files are generated and
made available for code completion.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed incorrect FSharp.Core NuGet package restored</strong></p>

<p>Installing the FSharp.Core
4.5.0 NuGet package into a F# .NET Core console project would result in
version 4.3.4 of the FSharp.Core NuGet
package being used and displayed in the Dependencies folder. FSharp.Core 4.3.4 is
the NuGet package implicitly added by the F# .NET Core SDK. This was being used by
the project instead of the PackageReference defined in the project.
PackageReferences in the project will now override any implicitly
added NuGet packages. This matches the behaviour of dotnet restore when
run from the command line.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed updating PackageReference removing metadata</strong></p>

<p>On updating a NuGet PackageReference the old PackageReference was
removed from the project file and then a new PackageReference was added.
This resulted in custom MSBuild properties associated with the
PackageReference being removed from the project file.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;PackageReference Include="NuGet.Versioning" Version="3.6.0"&gt;
  &lt;PrivateAssets&gt;all&lt;/PrivateAssets&gt;
&lt;/PackageReference&gt;  
</code></pre>

<p>Now on updating a NuGet package the version of the existing PackageReference element
is updated so any custom MSBuild properties are not removed.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed build error after updating Xamarin.Forms PackageReference</strong></p>

<p>A build error could occur after updating projects that had
a Xamarin.Forms PackageReference. One way to reproduce this was to
have a .NET Standard project that used an old Xamarin.Forms
version as a PackageReference, and another non .NET Core project,
that references the .NET Standard project, which used a newer
Xamarin.Forms NuGet package. On building an
error would be displayed:</p>

<pre><code>Error XF002: Xamarin.Forms tasks do not match targets
</code></pre>

<p>On updating the .NET Standard project to use the same Xamarin.Forms
NuGet package version the build error would still occur until the solution
was closed and re-opened. Now the remote MSBuild host is shutdown
to ensure the correct Xamarin.Forms MSBuild targets and assemblies
are used after the NuGet package is updated.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed build error after updating Xamarin.Forms NuGet package</strong></p>

<p>On updating the Xamarin.Forms NuGet package in a solution
the build would sometimes fail with errors similar to:</p>

<pre><code>Could not load file or assembly 'Xamarin.Forms.Xaml,
Version=2.0.0.0, Culture=neutral, PublicKeyToken=null' or one of
its dependencies.

Error XF002: Xamarin.Forms tasks do not match targets. Please
ensure that all projects reference the same version of
Xamarin.Forms, and if the error persists, please restart the IDE.
</code></pre>

<p>The problem was that the old MSBuild tasks and targets from the originally used
Xamarin.Forms NuGet package were
still being used. Now when an MSBuild import has changed in a project
the remote MSBuild host is shutdown to ensure the correct MSBuild tasks are
used.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed editor errors when .NET Standard assembly referenced in Xamarin.iOS project</strong></p>

<p>When a Xamarin.iOS project used an assembly that was compiled
for .NET Standard, such as the assembly in the
System.Collections.Immutable NuGet package, the netstandard assembly
was not made available for code completion. This then resulted in the text editor
showing errors even though the project could be compiled succesfully.
The errors displayed were similar to:</p>

<pre><code>  The type 'ValueType' is defined in an assembly that is not
  referenced. You must add a reference to assembly 'netstandard,
  Version=2.0.0.0, Culture=neutral, PublicKeytoken=cc7b1dffcd2ddd51'.
</code></pre>

<p>Now a check is made to determine
if an assembly is referencing netstandard and if so the facade assemblies,
which for Xamarin.iOS will include the netstandard.dll, are made available
for code completion. Previously only a check was made for the project having
an assembly referencing System.Runtime before including the facade assemblies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.NET Core Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.5]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/05/20/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-20T09:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/05/20/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>New Features</h2>

<ul>
<li>.NET Core 2.1 SDK support

<ul>
<li>.NET Core 2.1 SDK project templates</li>
<li>HTTPS development certificate support</li>
<li>.NET Core global tools added to PATH on startup</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>.NET Core location can now be configured</li>
<li>Xamarin.Forms project templates now use .NET Standard projects</li>
<li>Performance improvements when using projects with many files</li>
<li>.NET Core templating engine has been updated</li>
<li>Improved support for Xamarin.Forms</li>
<li>Item templates are now supported with the .NET Core templating engine</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.5</a> can be found in the
<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#-visual-studio-2017-for-mac-version-75-release-notes">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>.NET Core 2.1 SDK support</h2>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac 7.5 includes support for the .NET Core 2.1 SDK which is currently
available as a <a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2018/05/07/announcing-net-core-2-1-rc-1/">release candidate</a>. The following
sections will look into the support provided by Visual Studio for Mac 7.5 for the .NET Core 2.1 SDK.</p>

<h3>.NET Core 2.1 SDK project templates</h3>

<p>If .NET Core 2.1.300 SDK is installed then the .NET Core 2.1 project templates
will be available in the New Project dialog.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/NewProjectDialogNetCore21TargetFramework.png" title="New Project dialog - .NET Core 2.1 target framework option" alt="New Project dialog - .NET Core 2.1 target framework option"></p>

<p>The .NET Core 2.1 project templates are not included with Visual Studio for Mac and
will be searched for in the 2.1.300 SDK templates directory.</p>

<pre><code>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/2.1.300-rc1-008673/Templates/
</code></pre>

<p>The project templates for .NET Core 2.0 and 1.1 are currently still being shipped
with Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<h3>HTTPS development certificate support</h3>

<p>ASP.NET Core 2.1 projects use HTTPS by default. In order to be able to run
ASP.NET Core 2.1 projects with HTTPS a development certificate needs to be installed.
Visual Studio for Mac will detect if the development certificate is missing
and offer to install it when you run an ASP.NET Core 2.1 project that uses
HTTPS.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/HttpsDevCertificateNotInstalledMessage.png" title="HTTPS development certificate not installed message" alt="HTTPS development certificate not installed message"></p>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac will use the dotnet dev-certs tool to check if the
HTTPS development certificate is installed and trusted.</p>

<pre><code>dotnet dev-certs https --trust --check
</code></pre>

<p>Installing the HTTPS certificate requires administrator privileges so you may be
prompted for your username and password after clicking the Yes button. Currently
the prompt for credentials shows <strong>mono-sgen64 wants to make changes</strong>. In the future this will show a
custom message indicating that the credentials are required to install the HTTPS development certificate.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/MonoSGenAdminPrompt.png" title="Mono sgen administrator dialog prompt" alt="Mono sgen administrator dialog prompt"></p>

<p>After entering your credentials the following command is run as administrator.</p>

<pre><code>dotnet dev-certs https --trust
</code></pre>

<p>After the certificate is installed the ASP.NET Core 2.1 project will be
opened in the default browser using HTTPS.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/AspNetCoreProjectInChromeUsingHttps.png" title="ASP.NET Core 2.1 project open in browser using HTTPS" alt="ASP.NET Core 2.1 project open in browser using HTTPS"></p>

<p>Running <strong>dotnet dev-certs https &mdash;trust</strong> to install and trust the certificate needs to be
done with administrator privileges with the user id 0. To do this Visual Studio for Mac
does the following:</p>

<ol>
<li>Launches a separate custom console app.</li>
<li>The console app uses the AuthorizationExecuteWithPrivileges Mac
API provided by Xamarin.Mac to launch itself as again as administrator.
It is not possible to run dotnet as administrator initially since it requires the user id to be
set to 0, which is what happens when you use <strong>sudo dotnet</strong>, and this can only be done
when running with administrator privileges. So the console app is launched again but this
time with administrator privileges.</li>
<li>The console app, now being run with administrator privileges, will use setuid to set the
current user id to 0.</li>
<li>The console app then runs <strong>dotnet dev-certs https &mdash;trust</strong> which
will install and trust the HTTPS development certificate.</li>
</ol>


<p>The <strong>dotnet dev-certs https &mdash;trust</strong> command will add two localhost certificates. You
can see these by opening the Keychain Access application and searching for
localhost.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/LocalhostCertificateInKeychain.png" title="localhost certificate created by dotnet dev-certs in Keychain Access application" alt="localhost certificate created by dotnet dev-certs in Keychain Access application"></p>

<p>If the HTTPS development certificate is found to be valid and
trusted then this will be remembered for the current Visual Studio for Mac
session and a check will not be run again during the current session.</p>

<h3>.NET Core global tools added to path on startup</h3>

<p>The .NET Core SDK 2.1 supports installing global tools. These tools are .NET Core console apps
that are available as NuGet packages and can be installed and used from the command line.
To be able to use these tools with the dotnet command line the <strong>~/.dotnet/tools</strong>
directory needs to be added to the PATH environment variable. The path to
these global tools is now added to Visual Studio&rsquo;s PATH environment variable
when it starts.</p>

<h3>Prompt to install .NET Core 2.1 SDK if not installed</h3>

<p>If a .NET Core 2.1 project is opened and .NET Core 2.1.300 SDK is not
installed then a dialog will be shown allowing the SDK to
be downloaded. The project in the Solution window will show an error
icon indicating that the .NET Core 2.1 SDK is not
installed.</p>

<h3>Launching a browser when running an ASP.NET Core 2.1 project</h3>

<p>The .NET Core SDK 2.1 project templates for ASP.NET Core
specify the https and http urls in the launchSettings.json file
by using the applicationUrl property.</p>

<pre><code>    "MyAspNetCore21Project": {
        "commandName": "Project",
        "launchBrowser": true,
        "applicationUrl": "https://localhost:5001;http://localhost:5000",
        "environmentVariables": {
            "ASPNETCORE_ENVIRONMENT": "Development"
        }
    }
</code></pre>

<p>With earlier .NET Core 2.1 preview SDKs this was defined in the
ASPNETCORE_URLS environment variable. The full applicationUrl
property was used unmodified when running the ASP.NET Core 2.1 project and
resulted in an invalid url being used causing the AspNetCoreExecutionHandler to log a warning
and not opening the browser. Now the first url in the applicationUrl
is used if there are multiple urls.</p>

<h3>Support ASPNETCORE_URLS when launching the browser</h3>

<p>If the launchSettings.json does not define an applicationUrl then
Visual Studio for Mac will fallback to checking the environment variable defined
for ASPNETCORE_URLS in the launchSettings.json file and will use the first url
found there. This url will be used to launch the browser when running the project.</p>

<p>An example launchSettings.json that was used in the .NET Core 2.1 preview SDKs
is shown below.</p>

<pre><code>"MyProject": {
  "commandName": "Project",
  "launchBrowser": true,
  "environmentVariables": {
    "ASPNETCORE_ENVIRONMENT": "Development",
    "ASPNETCORE_URLS": "https://localhost:5001;http://localhost:5000"
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Compared with the .NET Core SDK 2.0.</p>

<pre><code>"MyProject": {
  "commandName": "Project",
  "launchBrowser": true,
  "environmentVariables": {
    "ASPNETCORE_ENVIRONMENT": "Development"
  },
  "applicationUrl": "http://localhost:5000/"
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Allow .NET Core location to be configured</h2>

<p>In Preferences there is now a Projects &ndash; SDK Locations &ndash; .NET Core
section that can be used to configure the location of the .NET Core
command line tool (dotnet).</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/NetCoreLocationConfiguration.png" title=".NET Core location configured in preferences" alt=".NET Core location configured in preferneces"></p>

<p>This can be used to configure Visual Studio for Mac to use a
.NET Core SDK that is not installed in the default location. After this is
changed the MSBuild engine hosts are recycled and all .NET Core projects
are re-evaluated to ensure the new locations of any MSBuild targets
are used.</p>

<p>If the location is invalid, or no runtimes or SDKs can be found at the configured
location, a Not found error will be displayed.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/NetCoreLocationInvalidPath.png" title="Invalid .NET Core location path specified in preferences" alt="Invalid .NET Core location path specified in preferences"></p>

<h2>Xamarin.Forms Project Templates now include .NET Standard projects</h2>

<p>The Xamarin.Forms project templates, Blank Forms App and Forms App, will now
create a .NET Standard 2.0 project instead of a Portable Class Library (PCL) project
if .NET Standard is selected in the New Project dialog.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/NewProjectDialogFormsNetStandard.png" title="New Project dialog - Blank Forms - .NET Standard option" alt="New Project dialog - Blank Forms - .NET Standard option"></p>

<p>The Xamarin.Forms Class Library project template now creates a .NET Standard 2.0 project instead of
a Portable Class Library project.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/NewProjectDialogXamarinFormsLibraryProject.png" title="New Project dialog - Xamarin.Forms Class Library project" alt="New Project dialog - Xamarin.Forms Class Library project"></p>

<h2>Prevent .xaml.cs file from being renamed in a .NET Core project</h2>

<p>The Xamarin.Forms NuGet package has an MSBuild .targets file that is imported
after the project items are defined. This .targets file overrides
the DependentUpon property for all .xaml.cs files. This means that renaming the
.xaml.cs file to be different to the .xaml file is not supported.
To prevent this the Rename menu is now disabled in the Solution
window for .xaml.cs files if they depend on a .xaml file.</p>

<h2>Exclude None build action for XAML files in .NET Core projects</h2>

<p>Recent versions of Xamarin.Forms NuGet packages exclude all .xaml files from the
default None file wildcard defined by the .NET Core SDK. This exclusion is
done in a .targets file which is applied after the items in the project
file have been added. This means that a .NET Standard project should not use
None items for .xaml files since they will be removed. To avoid this problem
the None build action is excluded from the list of build actions for .xaml files.
This list of build actions is available when right
clicking the file in the Solution window and in the Properties window when
the file is selected.</p>

<h2>Dependent files now renamed on renaming parent file in the Solution window</h2>

<p>When a file is renamed in the Solution window the dependent files will
also be renamed if they start with the same name as the parent file.
This avoids problems with XAML files since a different name for the .xaml file
and the associated .xaml.cs file is not supported.</p>

<h2>Improve project load times for projects with many files</h2>

<p>Opening a .NET Core project that contained many files that
were not excluded, such as a .NET Core console project that has a
node_modules directory, could take a long time to load.</p>

<p>Some performance improvements have been made to speed up the
loading of .NET Core projects. For a .NET Core console project that had a node_modules
directory containing around 17000 files the initial project load time which
was taking around 70-80 seconds and now it takes around 20 seconds. Visual Studio 2017 on
Windows takes around 15-20 seconds to load the same project before
it is visible in the Solution Explorer window.</p>

<p>The performance improvements include:</p>

<ol>
<li>Adding a faster project item lookup used when finding an existing
project item on loading the project.</li>
<li>Updating the existing project items is now faster avoiding iterating
over the existing items.</li>
<li>Evaluating MSBuild items is now only done when evaluating properties.
Previously this was done when evaluating project configurations and run configurations.
This would result in
files and directories being searched multiple times when looking
wildcard matches on loading the project. Now the files
and directories are searched once during the initial project load.</li>
</ol>


<h2>.NET Core templating engine updated</h2>

<p>Updated the .NET Core templating to version 1.0.0-beta3-20171117-314. This new
version of the .NET Core templating engine fixes the following problems:</p>

<ol>
<li>Templates that use files with @ character in their names being generated with the
@ symbol encoded.</li>
<li>Templates that use the Guid macro and did not specify a format
would cause the template generation to fail. An exception was thrown
since the format was not defined. Now
if the format is not defined the default format is used.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Report template creation failures when using the .NET Core templating engine</h2>

<p>To help diagnose problems with project and item templates that use the
.NET Core templating engine more detailed information about the failure is now logged
in the IDE log.</p>

<h2>Support item templates with the new templating engine</h2>

<p>Item templates that use the .NET Core
templating engine can be defined through a new extension point.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Extension path="/MonoDevelop/Ide/ItemTemplates"&gt;
        &lt;Template
                id="Azure.Function.CSharp.BlobTrigger"
                _overrideName="Blob Trigger"
                path="Templates/Azure.Functions.Templates.nupkg" /&gt;
&lt;/Extension&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Item templates are not currently supported in the New File dialog however there
is an API that can be used by extensions to create files from these templates.
This is currently used when adding a new Azure Function to a project.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Missing child package dependencies in Solution window</strong></p>

<p>After creating a new ASP.NET Core project sometimes the package dependencies
shown in the Solution window under the SDK folder and the NuGet folder
could not be expanded to view the child dependencies.</p>

<p>The problem was that if the call to get the package dependencies
using MSBuild was cancelled this would result an empty list of depenencies
being cached. Since no package dependencies were returned the Solution window
would fallback to showing the package dependencies that were listed in the
project and a default top level SDK package dependency.</p>

<p><strong>MSBuild wildcards being expanded on saving a project</strong></p>

<p>Saving a project with a file wildcard that had a Link with
MSBuild item metadata, as shown below, would result in the wildcard
being removed and replaced with MSBuild items for each file included
by the wildcard.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Compile Include="**\*.cs" Exclude="obj\**"&gt;
  &lt;Link&gt;%(RecursiveDir)%(Filename).cs&lt;/Link&gt;
&lt;/Compile&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The problem was that the evaluated Link property value was being
compared with the unevaluated value, which did not match, resulting
in the wildcard being replaced with individual MSBuild items for
each file. Now if the property value contains a % character a comparison is
made against the evaluated value when checking if the project item
has changed.</p>

<p><strong>MSBuild items added for wildcards with link metadata on saving project</strong></p>

<p>A project containing the following MSBuild file wildcards would have
extra MSBuild items added when the project file was saved.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ItemGroup&gt;
  &lt;Compile Include="..\**\*.cs"&gt;
    &lt;Link&gt;%(RecursiveDir)%(Filename)%(Extension)&lt;/Link&gt;
  &lt;/Compile&gt;
&lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>On saving the project Compile update items would be added for each
file included by the file wildcard.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ItemGroup&gt;
  &lt;Compile Update="..\Test\Class1.cs"&gt;
    &lt;Link&gt;Class1.cs&lt;/Link&gt;
  &lt;/Compile&gt;
&lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This problem is similar to the previous problem where the evaluated Link value was being
compared with the unevaluated value, which did not match, resulting
MSBuild update items being added to the project when it was saved. Now if the property
value contains a % character a comparison is made against the evaluated value when checking if
the project item has changed.</p>

<p><strong>TargetFramework changed on saving project</strong></p>

<p>Adding a file to an SDK style project that targeted Tizen 4.0 would
result in the TargetFramework changing from <strong>tizen40</strong> to <strong>tizen4.0</strong>.
Now the original framework identifier name is not modified and if
the version of the framework changes then the version will be
dotted or contain only numbers based on the format that was originally used
in the project file.</p>

<p><strong>ASP.NET Core file templates modifying project file</strong></p>

<p>Adding a new .cshtml file from a file template to an ASP.NET Core
project would modify the project file when it should not have been
modified. The problem was the files were added as None items whilst
.cshtml are Content items. The project file would contain the
following after adding a new cshtml file from a template:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ItemGroup&gt;
  &lt;Content Remove="Views\Index.cshtml" /&gt;
&lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
&lt;ItemGroup&gt;
  &lt;None Include="Views\Index.cshtml" /&gt;
&lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Another problem was that the Razor Page with view model file
template specifies a DependentUpon property so this was added to the
project file. This would result in the .cshtml and .cs files being nested whilst
the other .cshtml and .cs files created with the initial ASP.NET
Core project template were not nested. The project file would include
the following:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ItemGroup&gt;
  &lt;Compile Update="Views\Index.cshtml.cs"&gt;
    &lt;DependentUpon&gt;Index.cshtml&lt;/DependentUpon&gt;
  &lt;/Compile&gt;
&lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The .NET Core SDK does not indicate that .cshtml and .cs
files are dependent on each other so they are not currently nested
in the Solution window. New .cshtml files created from these updated
file templates will now not be nested in Solution window.</p>

<p><strong>XAML files not nested after editing project file in editor</strong></p>

<p>Adding a new content page with xaml to a .NET Standard project,
then excluding the files from the project, but not deleting it,
then editing the project file and commenting out the MSBuild remove
items, would then result in the xaml files not being nested in the
Solution window. The problem was that the MSBuild update item
for the .xaml.cs file, defined by the Xamarin.Forms default msbuild
items, was being removed from the MSBuild project in
memory. This MSBuild update item had the DependsOn property defined
so this information was lost on reloading the project. Now a check
is to made to ensure only update items that exist in the original
project file are removed.</p>

<p><strong>MSBuild item added for XAML file copied to a .NET Standard project</strong></p>

<p>When copying a .xaml file from a Portable Class Library project to a .NET Standard project
an MSBuild include item for the file would be added if the .xaml file did
not have the default metadata properties defined by Xamarin.Forms.
Now .NET Core projects opt-in to supporting items not being excluded if they
are missing MSBuild item metadata
which prevents an MSBuild include item added for the .xaml file.</p>

<p><strong>Duplicate XAML file build error when copying file to a .NET Standard project</strong></p>

<p>Copying a .xaml file from a Portable Class Library project to a .NET Standard project
would result an MSBuild item for the .xaml file to the project causing it to not
build due to a duplicate .xaml file.</p>

<p>Now when a xaml file is copied into a .NET Standard project, and it is missing
properties that are included in by an update wildcard,
an MSBuild item will not be added to the project.</p>

<p><strong>MSBuild remove item not added for .xaml.cs file</strong></p>

<p>With a .NET Core project, containing a single .xaml file and a
dependent .xaml.cs file, removing but not deleting the .xaml file
from the Solution window would not add an MSBuild remove item for
the .xaml.cs file even though it was removed from the Solution window.</p>

<p>The problem was that the Xamarin.Forms NuGet package includes a
Compile update item and only this was being considered when saving
the project file. The default file wildcard, that includes all .cs files,
provided by the .NET Core SDK was not considered. Only the last MSBuild item
associated with the .xaml.cs file was being considered. If there was another .cs
file in the project then the MSBuild remove item was added correctly. To avoid this
all MSBuild items associated with a project item are now considered.</p>

<p><strong>MSBuild remove item not removed on adding XAML file to project</strong></p>

<p>When an .xaml file was removed but not deleted, and Xamarin.Forms 2.5
used, which has default MSBuild items defined, on adding the .xaml
file back again to the project the EmbeddedResource
remove item was not removed from the project.</p>

<p>The problem was that the .xaml file was being added as a None item
since by default there is no build action specified for .xaml files.</p>

<p>Another problem was that the MSBuild remove
items, defined by Xamarin.Forms that remove all .xaml files from the default None
included by the .NET Core SDK, were being ignored since the file wildcards were not
found.</p>

<p>Also an msbuild item is no longer added for an existing xaml file when it is
added to the project. The Xamarin.Forms default msbuild items
for .xaml files have extra metadata which were not being added to
the file when it was added to the project from the file system.</p>

<p><strong>Update item added on renaming xaml.cs file</strong></p>

<p>When the .xaml and .xaml.cs file were renamed at the same time an
MSBuild update item was added for the .xaml.cs file even though the Xamarin
Forms NuGet package has a default MSBuild item that was the same as
the generated MSBuild update item.</p>

<p><strong>Argument null exception logged on opening .NET Core project</strong></p>

<p>Opening a .NET Core project would sometimes log an unhandled
ArgumentNullException. A file created event was sometimes raised before
the project had finished loading and could result in
a null set of items being used when checking if the
new file should be added to the project. This is now handled. The files being
created on project load are typically in the obj folder and would be
ignored by the default file wildcards.</p>

<pre><code>An unhandled exception has occured. Terminating Visual Studio? False
System.ArgumentNullException: Value cannot be null.
Parameter name: source
  at System.Linq.Enumerable.Where[TSource]
  in corefx/src/System.Linq/src/System/Linq/Where.cs:42
  at MonoDevelop.Projects.Project.OnFileCreatedExternally
in src/core/MonoDevelop.Core/MonoDevelop.Projects/Project.cs:4041
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NuGet Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.5]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/05/19/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-19T15:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/05/19/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> Support installing NuGet packages with item templates</li>
<li> Fixed generated NuGet package files not available for code completion</li>
<li> Fixed incorrect Android target framework used when the project has Package References</li>
<li> Fixed build errors after creating a new Android project with NuGet packages</li>
<li> Missing package dependencies in Solution window</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.5</a>
can be found in the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#-visual-studio-2017-for-mac-version-75-release-notes">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>Support installing NuGet packages with item templates</h2>

<p>Initial support for creating new files from item templates that use
the .NET Core templating engine has been added. This is currently used
by the Azure Functions support in Visual Studio for Mac when a new Azure
Function is added to the project. Currently the New File dialog does not
have support for showing these templates but there is an API that can
be used by extensions to create files from these templates.</p>

<p>The item templates can define post actions that indicate that a NuGet
package is needed. These post actions are read and the NuGet
package will be installed into the project by Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<pre><code>"postActions": [
  {
    "Description": "Adding Reference to Microsoft.Azure.WebJobs.Extensions.DocumentDB Nuget package",
    "ActionId": "B17581D1-C5C9-4489-8F0A-004BE667B814",
    "ContinueOnError": "true",
    "ManualInstructions": [],
    "args": {
      "referenceType": "package",
      "reference": "Microsoft.Azure.WebJobs.Extensions.DocumentDB",
      "version": "1.2.0",
      "projectFileExtensions": ".csproj"
    }
  }
</code></pre>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Generated NuGet package files not available for code completion</strong></p>

<p>On installing a NuGet package such as Refit, which extends the
CoreCompileDependsOn to generate a C# file, the generated file would
not be available for code completion until the solution was closed
and re-opened again.</p>

<p>Below is a section of the refit.targets file used by the Refit NuGet package.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;PropertyGroup&gt;
  &lt;CoreCompileDependsOn&gt;
    $(CoreCompileDependsOn);
    GenerateRefitStubs;
  &lt;/CoreCompileDependsOn&gt;
&lt;/PropertyGroup&gt;

&lt;Target Name="GenerateRefitStubs" BeforeTargets="CoreCompile"&gt;

  &lt;Error Condition="'$(MSBuildRuntimeType)' == 'Core' and '$(RefitMinCoreVersionRequired)' &gt; '$(RefitNetCoreAppVersion)' "
       Text="Refit requires at least the .NET Core SDK v2.0 to run with 'dotnet build'"
       ContinueOnError="false"
       /&gt;

  &lt;GenerateStubsTask SourceFiles="@(Compile)" BaseDirectory="$(MSBuildProjectDirectory)"   OutputFile="$(IntermediateOutputPath)\RefitStubs.g.cs" /&gt;

  &lt;Message Text="Processed Refit Stubs" /&gt;      

  &lt;ItemGroup Condition="Exists('$(IntermediateOutputPath)\RefitStubs.g.cs')"&gt;
    &lt;Compile Include="$(IntermediateOutputPath)\RefitStubs.g.cs" /&gt;
  &lt;/ItemGroup&gt;    
&lt;/Target&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The CoreCompileDependsOn property is re-defined so the GenerateRefitsStubs MSBuild
target will be run. This creates a new RefitStubs.g.cs file which is included in the
project by the Compile MSBuild item.</p>

<p>The problem was that the result of running the
targets that are defined by the CoreCompileDependsOn property are cached by Visual
Studio for Mac.
When Refit is installed the cached result was still being returned so the
generated C# file was not available for code completion. To fix this the
project is now re-evaluated before getting the CoreCompileDependsOn property
if an MSBuild import has been added or removed. Note that projects that use
Package References were unaffected. Only projects that use a packages.config
file were affected.</p>

<p><strong>Incorrect Android target framework used when the project has Package References</strong></p>

<p>Configuring an Android project so it uses the latest Android framework
could result in the wrong target framework being used when building if the
project used Package References. This would result in a build error
similar to:</p>

<pre><code>Error: Your project is not referencing the "MonoAndroid,Version=v7.1" framework. 
Add a reference to "MonoAndroid,Version=v7.1" in the "frameworks" section of your 
project.json, and then re-run NuGet restore
</code></pre>

<p>The problem was that the wrong target framework was being used in the
project.assets.json. Running a NuGet restore was
a workaround for the problem.</p>

<p>Now when the target framework version in project options is changed, and
the project uses Package References, a NuGet restore is run after the
project file is saved. This ensures the Package References work with
the new target framework. This also re-generates the project.assets.json file
so the build will use the correct references.</p>

<p>Another problem here was that configuring the Android to use the latest
target framework would not result in the target framework being changed
in the project model stored in memory.
This could also result in the project.assets.json file being out of
sync with the Android project&rsquo;s target framework.</p>

<p><strong>Build errors after creating a new Android project with NuGet packages</strong></p>

<p>Creating a new Android project that installed NuGet packages as it was created
would sometimes result in build errors that could be fixed by closing and
re-opening the solution. An example build error is shown below.</p>

<pre><code>Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 1: error: Error retrieving parent for item: No resource found that matches the given name 'Theme.AppCompat.Light.DarkActionBar'.
Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 2: error: Error: No resource found that matches the given   name: attr 'colorAccent'.
Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 1: error: Error: No resource found that matches the given name: attr 'colorPrimary'.
Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 1: error: Error: No resource found that matches the given name: attr 'colorPrimaryDark'.
Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 1: error: Error: No resource found that matches the given name: attr 'windowActionBar'.
Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 3: error: Error: No resource found that matches the given name: attr 'windowActionModeOverlay'.
Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 1: error: Error: No resource found that matches the given name: attr 'windowNoTitle'.
Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 3: error: Error retrieving parent for item: No resource found that matches the given name 'Theme.AppCompat.Light.Dialog'.
Resources/values/styles.xml : error APT0000: 3: error: Error: No resource found that matches the given name: attr 'colorAccent'.
</code></pre>

<p>The build errors varied but in each case the error was caused by a
missing reference to an assembly from one of the Android Support NuGet packages installed
when the project was created. The project file created would have
the correct reference information but Visual Studio for Mac was
building an old version of the project.</p>

<p>If the project was modified in memory when a build is requested this
results in the unsaved project xml being given to the remote MSBuild
host. In some cases this project xml was not being cleared and would
result in an out of date project xml being used when building. This
could occur if the MSBuild host did not have any projects
loaded at the time when an attempt was made to unload the project from
the host. Now the unsaved project xml is removed in all cases when the
project is unloaded from the MSBuild host.</p>

<p><strong>Missing package dependencies in Solution window</strong></p>

<p>After creating a new ASP.NET Core project sometimes the package dependencies
shown in the Solution window under the SDK folder and the NuGet folder
could not be expanded to view the child dependencies.</p>

<p>The problem was that if the call to get the package dependencies
using MSBuild was cancelled this would result an empty list of depenencies
being cached. Since no package dependencies were returned the Solution window
would fallback to showing the package dependencies that were listed in the
project and a default top level SDK package dependency.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Language Server Protocol support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.4]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/03/18/LanguageServerSupportInVisualStudioMac7-4/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-18T12:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/03/18/LanguageServerSupportInVisualStudioMac7-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A preview of support for the <a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/language-server-protocol">Language Server Protocol</a>
is now available for Visual Studio for Mac 7.4 as a separate extension.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/LanguageServerSupportInVisualStudioMac/DockerLanguageServerClient.gif" title="Docker Language Server client being used in Visual Studio for Mac" alt="Docker Language Server client being used in Visual Studio for Mac"></p>

<p>A Language Server can provide support for programming language features such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>Code completion</li>
<li>Find references</li>
<li>Go to definition</li>
<li>Quick fixes</li>
<li>Method signature help</li>
<li>Errors and warnings diagnostics</li>
<li>Documentation on hover</li>
<li>Document formatting</li>
<li>Rename refactoring</li>
</ul>


<p>The <a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/language-server-protocol">Language Server Protocol</a> provides a way for a
client application, such as Visual Studio for Mac, to communicate with the Language Server in order to
use the programming language features it supports.</p>

<p><a href="https://code.visualstudio.com">Visual Studio Code</a> supports the
<a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/blogs/2016/06/27/common-language-protocol">Language Server Protocol</a>.</p>

<p>A preview of <a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/visualstudio/2017/11/21/announcing-language-server-protocol-preview-release/">Language Server Protocol support in Visual Studio 2017 on Windows</a>
has also been announced.</p>

<p>Currently there is no support for debugging. Whilst there is a
<a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/extensionAPI/api-debugging">debugging protocol</a> support
for this is not currently available in Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<p>The Language Server Protocol does not provide any support for compiling the code. This would need
to be provided by the extension that implements the language client.</p>

<p>More detailed information about the Language Server Protocol can be found on the
<a href="https://microsoft.github.io/language-server-protocol/">Language Server Protocol site</a>.</p>

<p>The <strong>Creating a Language Client</strong> section below will take a more detailed look at how to implement
a custom Language Server Client extension in Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<h2>Supports</h2>

<ul>
<li>MonoDevelop or Visual Studio Mac 7.4 or later.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Source Code</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-language-server-addin">Language Server Client extension for Visual Studio for Mac and MonoDevelop</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>The Language Server Client extension is available to download from <a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-language-server-addin/releases/download/0.1-monodevelop-7.4/MonoDevelop.LanguageServer.Client_0.1.mpack">GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>To install the extension open the Extensions Manager by selecting Extensions&hellip; from the main menu. Click the Install from file button. Select the .mpack file and then click the Open button.</p>

<p>The extension is also available in the Extensions Manager from the
<a href="http://addins.monodevelop.com/Project/Index/307">Visual Studio Extension Repository (Beta channel)</a>.</p>

<h2>Creating a Language Client</h2>

<p>The API provided by the Language Server Client extension follows the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/extensibility/adding-an-lsp-extension">API defined by the
Language Server Protocol extension used by Visual Studio on Windows</a> as
closely as possible.</p>

<p>More detailed documentation on the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/extensibility/language-server-protocol">Language Server Client API</a> provided
by Visual Studio on Windows is available from the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/extensibility/language-server-protocol">Microsoft docs site</a>.</p>

<h3>Prerequisites</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-language-server-addin">Language Server Client Extension</a> for
Visual Studio for Mac should be installed.</p>

<p>Also ensure you have the <a href="https://github.com/mhutch/MonoDevelop.AddinMaker">Addin Maker extension installed</a>.
This can be installed by selecting Extensions&hellip; from the main menu top open the Extensions Manager.
Select the Gallery tab and use the text box at the top right to search for the Addin Maker extension.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/LanguageServerSupportInVisualStudioMac/ExtensionsDialogAddinMaker.png" title="Addin maker selected in Extensions Manager dialog" alt="Addin maker selected in Extensions Manager dialog"></p>

<p>Click the Install button to install the Addin Maker extension.</p>

<p>The Addin Maker will be used to create the language client extension.</p>

<h3>Creating an IDE Extension project</h3>

<p>The starting point is to create an IDE Extension project. This project template is provided by the
Addin Maker extension and is available
from the New Project dialog, in the Other &ndash; IDE Extensions category.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/LanguageServerSupportInVisualStudioMac/NewProjectDialogIdeExtension.png" title="IDE Extension project selected in New Project dialog" alt="IDE Extension project selected in New Project dialog"></p>

<p>After creating the IDE Extensions project, expand the Dependencies folder to show the
Extensions folder. Right click the Extensions folder and select Add Addin Reference.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/LanguageServerSupportInVisualStudioMac/NewProjectDialogIdeExtension.png" title="IDE Extension project selected in New Project dialog" alt="IDE Extension project selected in New Project dialog"></p>

<p>Find the MonoDevelop.LanguageServer.Client in the Add Extension Reference dialog. Select it to
toggle its check box and then click the Add button to reference it.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/LanguageServerSupportInVisualStudioMac/AddExtensionReferenceDialogLanguageServerClient.png" title="Language Server Client extension in Add Extension Reference dialog" alt="Language Server Client extension in Add Extension Reference dialog"></p>

<p>There are three parts to implementing a language client:</p>

<ul>
<li>Enabling <a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/vs-mef">Managed Extensibility Framework (MEF)</a> support</li>
<li>Defining the supported content
types</li>
<li>Implementing the ILanguageClient interface.</li>
</ul>


<p>First we will take a look at enabling MEF support.</p>

<h3>Enabling Managed Extensibility Framework Support</h3>

<p>Registration of the language client with Visual Studio for Mac is done using the <a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/vs-mef">Managed Extensibility Framework (MEF)</a>
which is supported by Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<p>In order to use MEF in your language client extension you need to indicate to Visual Studio
for Mac that it should scan your extension for dependencies. This can be done in the
extension&rsquo;s .addin.xml file by adding the filename of your assembly.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;Extension path="/MonoDevelop/Ide/Composition"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;Assembly file="MockLanguageExtension.dll" /&gt;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/Extension&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Content Type Definition</h3>

<p>Your language client needs to indicate what files are supported. This is done by defining
a content type definition.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>using System.ComponentModel.Composition;
</span><span class='line'>using Microsoft.VisualStudio.LanguageServer.Client;
</span><span class='line'>using Microsoft.VisualStudio.Utilities;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>namespace MockLanguageExtension
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  #pragma warning disable CS0649 // Field is never assigned to.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  public class FooContentDefinition
</span><span class='line'>  {
</span><span class='line'>      [Export]
</span><span class='line'>      [Name("foo")]
</span><span class='line'>      [BaseDefinition(CodeRemoteContentDefinition.CodeRemoteContentTypeName)]
</span><span class='line'>      internal static ContentTypeDefinition FooContentTypeDefinition;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      [Export]
</span><span class='line'>      [FileExtension(".foo")]
</span><span class='line'>      [ContentType("foo")]
</span><span class='line'>      internal static FileExtensionToContentTypeDefinition FooFileExtensionDefinition;
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  #pragma warning restore CS0649
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The above content definition indicates that the .foo file extension is supported by the language client.</p>

<p>You can also define a filename, instead of a file extension, as supported by the language client by using
the FileName attribute instead of the FileExtension attribute.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>class DockerContentTypeDefinition
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  [Export]
</span><span class='line'>  [Name("docker")]
</span><span class='line'>  [BaseDefinition(CodeRemoteContentDefinition.CodeRemoteContentTypeName)]
</span><span class='line'>  internal static ContentTypeDefinition contentTypeDefinition;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  [Export]
</span><span class='line'>  [FileName("Dockerfile")]
</span><span class='line'>  [ContentType("docker")]
</span><span class='line'>  internal static FileExtensionToContentTypeDefinition dockerFileDefinition;
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>You will need to add a reference to <strong>System.ComponentModel.Composition</strong> so the <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/library/system.componentmodel.composition.exportattribute.aspx">Export attribute</a>
can be used.</p>

<h3>Implementing ILanguageClient</h3>

<p>To integrate the Language Server with Visual Studio for Mac the
<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/microsoft.visualstudio.languageserver.client.ilanguageclient">ILanguageClient interface</a>
needs to be implemented.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
<span class='line-number'>35</span>
<span class='line-number'>36</span>
<span class='line-number'>37</span>
<span class='line-number'>38</span>
<span class='line-number'>39</span>
<span class='line-number'>40</span>
<span class='line-number'>41</span>
<span class='line-number'>42</span>
<span class='line-number'>43</span>
<span class='line-number'>44</span>
<span class='line-number'>45</span>
<span class='line-number'>46</span>
<span class='line-number'>47</span>
<span class='line-number'>48</span>
<span class='line-number'>49</span>
<span class='line-number'>50</span>
<span class='line-number'>51</span>
<span class='line-number'>52</span>
<span class='line-number'>53</span>
<span class='line-number'>54</span>
<span class='line-number'>55</span>
<span class='line-number'>56</span>
<span class='line-number'>57</span>
<span class='line-number'>58</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>using System;
</span><span class='line'>using System.Collections.Generic;
</span><span class='line'>using System.ComponentModel.Composition;
</span><span class='line'>using System.Diagnostics;
</span><span class='line'>using System.IO;
</span><span class='line'>using System.Threading;
</span><span class='line'>using System.Threading.Tasks;
</span><span class='line'>using Microsoft.VisualStudio.LanguageServer.Client;
</span><span class='line'>using Microsoft.VisualStudio.Threading;
</span><span class='line'>using Microsoft.VisualStudio.Utilities;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>namespace MockLanguageExtension
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  [ContentType("foo")]
</span><span class='line'>  [Export(typeof(ILanguageClient))]
</span><span class='line'>  public class FooLanguageClient : ILanguageClient
</span><span class='line'>  {
</span><span class='line'>      public IEnumerable&lt;string&gt; ConfigurationSections =&gt; null;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      public object InitializationOptions =&gt; null;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      public IEnumerable&lt;string&gt; FilesToWatch =&gt; null;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      public string Name =&gt; "Foo Language Extension";
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      public event AsyncEventHandler&lt;EventArgs&gt; StartAsync;
</span><span class='line'>      public event AsyncEventHandler&lt;EventArgs&gt; StopAsync;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      public async Task OnLoadedAsync()
</span><span class='line'>      {
</span><span class='line'>          await StartAsync?.InvokeAsync(this, EventArgs.Empty);
</span><span class='line'>      }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      public Task&lt;Connection&gt; ActivateAsync(CancellationToken token)
</span><span class='line'>      {
</span><span class='line'>          var info = new ProcessStartInfo();
</span><span class='line'>          var programPath = Path.Combine(Path.GetDirectoryName(GetType().Assembly.Location), "server", @"LanguageServer.UI.exe");
</span><span class='line'>          info.FileName = "mono";
</span><span class='line'>          info.Arguments = programPath;
</span><span class='line'>          info.WorkingDirectory = Path.GetDirectoryName(programPath);
</span><span class='line'>          info.UseShellExecute = false;
</span><span class='line'>          info.RedirectStandardInput = true;
</span><span class='line'>          info.RedirectStandardOutput = true;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>          var process = new Process();
</span><span class='line'>          process.StartInfo = info;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>          Connection connection = null;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>          if (process.Start())
</span><span class='line'>          {
</span><span class='line'>              connection = new Connection(process.StandardOutput.BaseStream, process.StandardInput.BaseStream);
</span><span class='line'>          }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>          return Task.FromResult(connection);
</span><span class='line'>      }
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The class that implements the ILanguageClient interface needs to indicate it supports
the content types that you have defined, and it also needs to indicate that it implements the
ILanguageClient by using the Export attribute.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>[ContentType("foo")]
</span><span class='line'>[Export(typeof(ILanguageClient))]</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The language client should return a unique description for the ILanguageClient.Name
property.</p>

<p>The two methods that should be implemented are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/microsoft.visualstudio.languageserver.client.ilanguageclient.onloadedasync">OnLoadedAsync</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/microsoft.visualstudio.languageserver.client.ilanguageclient.activateasync">ActivateAsync</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>OnLoadedAsync is called when Visual Studio for Mac has loaded your extension. To activate
your Language Server you need to call StartAsync. The simplest approach is to call StartAsync
in the OnLoadedAsync method.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'> public async Task OnLoadedAsync()
</span><span class='line'>  {
</span><span class='line'>      await StartAsync?.InvokeAsync(this, EventArgs.Empty);
</span><span class='line'>  }</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Calling StartAsync will cause Visual Studio for Mac to call the ILanguageClient&rsquo;s
ActivateAsync method. This is where you can start the Language Server.</p>

<p>The ActivateAsync method should return a Connection object with the streams that
will be used to communicate with the Language Server. Standard input and output streams
are supported as well as sockets.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>var connection = new Connection(process.StandardOutput.BaseStream, process.StandardInput.BaseStream);</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The first time you try to run and debug your language client extension you will see an error
in the Application Output similar to:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>WARNING: The add-in 'MockLanguageExtension,1.0' could not be updated because some of its 
</span><span class='line'>dependencies are missing or not compatible:
</span><span class='line'>  missing: MonoDevelop.LanguageServer.Client,0.1</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The Addin Maker runs your language client extension using its own extension database. The
MonoDevelop.LanguageServer.Client extension needs to be installed into this separate database
in order to be able to run and debug your language client extension.</p>

<p>To do this run your language client extension project in Visual Studio for Mac and
install the Language Server Client extension using the Extensions Manager in the instance
of Visual Studio for Mac that is started. Then stop debugging and re-run your extension project
again, and your language client should now be used when you open a supported file.</p>

<p>The content type registration and the ILanguageClient implementation is the minimum
that is needed in order to integrate your Language Server with Visual Studio for Mac.
Now let us take a look at other optional things that can be implemented.</p>

<h3>Receiving Custom Messages</h3>

<p>Your Language Server may support messages that are not part of the standard
Language Server Protocol.</p>

<p>In order to support receiving custom messages the class that implements ILanguageClient should also
implement the
<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/microsoft.visualstudio.languageserver.client.ilanguageclientcustommessage">ILanguageClientCustomMessage</a>
interface. The CustomMessageTarget property should return an object that will receive the messages.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>public object CustomMessageTarget =&gt; new CustomMessageTarget ();
</span><span class='line'>public object MiddleLayer =&gt; null;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>public Task AttachForCustomMessageAsync(JsonRpc rpc)
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  return Task.CompletedTask;
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>An example CustomMessageTarget class is shown below.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>using Newtonsoft.Json.Linq;
</span><span class='line'>using StreamJsonRpc;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>namespace MockLanguageExtension
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  public class CustomMessageTarget
</span><span class='line'>  {
</span><span class='line'>      [JsonRpcMethod("test/customNotification")]
</span><span class='line'>      public void OnCustomNotification(JToken arg)
</span><span class='line'>      {
</span><span class='line'>          // Handle custom message from the Language Server.
</span><span class='line'>      }
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Sending Custom Messages</h3>

<p>To send custom messages to the Language Server the class that implements the
ILanguageClient interface should also implement the
<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/microsoft.visualstudio.languageserver.client.ilanguageclientcustommessage">ILanguageClientCustomMessage</a> interface.</p>

<p>The AttachForCustomMessageAsync method
should save the JsonRpc object passed and then you can use the JsonRpc object to
send custom messages to the Language Server.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'> JsonRpc rpc;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  public Task AttachForCustomMessageAsync(JsonRpc rpc)
</span><span class='line'>  {
</span><span class='line'>      this.rpc = rpc;
</span><span class='line'>      return Task.CompletedTask;
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  public async Task SendMessageToServer()
</span><span class='line'>  {
</span><span class='line'>      string text = await rpc.InvokeWithParameterObjectAsync&lt;string&gt;("GetText");
</span><span class='line'>      MessageService.ShowMessage("Text from language server:", text);
</span><span class='line'>  }</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Middle Layer</h3>

<p>The ILanguageClientCustomMessage defines a MiddleLayer property. An object returned
from the MiddleLayer property can be used to intercept messages sent to and received
from the Language Server. The MiddleLayer object can implement the following
interfaces:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/microsoft.visualstudio.languageserver.client.ilanguageclientcompletionprovider">ILanguageClientCompletionProvider</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/microsoft.visualstudio.languageserver.client.ilanguageclientexecutecommandprovider">ILanguageClientExecuteCommandProvider</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/api/microsoft.visualstudio.languageserver.client.ilanguageclientworkspacesymbolprovider">ILanguageClientWorkspaceSymbolProvider</a></li>
</ul>


<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>using System;
</span><span class='line'>using System.Threading.Tasks;
</span><span class='line'>using Microsoft.VisualStudio.LanguageServer.Client;
</span><span class='line'>using Microsoft.VisualStudio.LanguageServer.Protocol;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>namespace MockLanguageExtension
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  class MiddleLayerProvider : ILanguageClientCompletionProvider
</span><span class='line'>  {
</span><span class='line'>      public Task&lt;object&gt; RequestCompletions(
</span><span class='line'>          TextDocumentPositionParams param,
</span><span class='line'>          Func&lt;TextDocumentPositionParams, Task&lt;object&gt;&gt; sendRequest)
</span><span class='line'>      {
</span><span class='line'>          return sendRequest(param);
</span><span class='line'>      }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      public async Task&lt;CompletionItem&gt; ResolveCompletion(
</span><span class='line'>          CompletionItem item,
</span><span class='line'>          Func&lt;CompletionItem, Task&lt;CompletionItem&gt;&gt; sendRequest)
</span><span class='line'>      {
</span><span class='line'>          return await sendRequest(item);
</span><span class='line'>      }
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Note that currently not all the Language Server messages can be intercepted.</p>

<p>The full source code to the sample Language Server Client Extension created
whilst writing this blog post is available on
<a href="https://github.com/mrward/sample-language-server-client-extension">GitHub</a></p>

<p>There are other examples included with the
<a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-language-server-addin">Language Server Client extension source code</a>
on GitHub, however these are not standalone and are compiled with the
Language Server Client extension.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.NET Core Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.4]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/03/11/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-4/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-11T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/03/11/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> Solution window detects file system changes outside Visual Studio for Mac</li>
<li> Projects with unknown target frameworks can now be loaded

<ul>
<li><a href="https://oren.codes/2017/08/29/use-all-tfms-with-sdk-style-projects-in-visual-studio-for-mac/">MSBuild SDK Extras</a> is now supported without requiring an extra extension to be installed</li>
<li>Tizen.NET projects are now supported</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> Fixed xUnit test messages not being displayed</li>
<li> ASP.NET Core minified files are no longer formatted</li>
<li> Support target framework defined in another MSBuild property</li>
<li> Show SDK information before dependencies are restored</li>
<li> Fixed failure to add new file when the default project namespace contains only numbers</li>
<li> Fixed remove item not added for .xaml.cs file</li>
<li> Fixed incorrect project updates when moving a file</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.4</a> can be found in the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#15.6">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>Solution window detects file system changes</h2>

<p>Files created in the project directory, or a subdirectory,
outside Visual Studio for Mac are now added to the project and
appear in the Solution window automatically.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-4/DotNetCoreProjectFileWatcher.gif" title="File added and removed from command line - Solution window updated" alt="File added and removed from command line - Solution window updated"></p>

<p>Deleting project files and directories will remove the files from
the Solution window. The Solution window will also update after
a file or a directory is renamed outside Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<h2>Allow unknown target framework projects to be loaded</h2>

<p>The target framework of an SDK style project is no longer restricted.
Previously Visual Studio for Mac would fail to load an SDK style
project unless its target framework was .NET Standard, .NET Core App
or .NET Framework.</p>

<p>This allows Tizen projects to be loaded without the error message
&ldquo;Project does not support framework &lsquo;Tizen,Version=v4.0&rsquo;&rdquo; being
displayed. Tizen projects have a Tizen.NET package reference which
imports an MSBuild .props file that defines the Tizen target framework.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/onovotny/MSBuildSdkExtras">MSBuild.Sdk.Extras</a> NuGet
package is now supported so SDK style projects can use target frameworks
that this NuGet package
supports, such as Xamarin.iOS and MonoAndroid.</p>

<p>On building a project with an unknown target framework, that is
not defined by any used NuGet package references, a build error
that indicates the framework is not supported will occur:</p>

<pre><code>The TargetFramework value 'test1.0' was not recognized.
</code></pre>

<p>NuGet restore will also fail for an unknown target framework with
a message indicating the framework is invalid.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Fix xUnit test messages not displayed</strong></p>

<p>xUnit tests support an ITestOutputHelper interface which can be
passed to the constructor of the test. This has a WriteLine method
which can be used to output messages whilst running the test. When
this was used the text displayed in Visual Studio for Mac&rsquo;s Test Results
window was:</p>

<pre><code>Microsoft.VisualStudio.TestPlatform.ObjectModel.TestResultMessage
</code></pre>

<p>Now the text from the message is shown in the Tests Results window.</p>

<p><strong>Support target framework defined in another MSBuild property</strong></p>

<p>An SDK style project that defined the <TargetFrameworks> element to
be another MSBuild property would fail to restore.</p>

<p>In the example below the property TheFramework is defined in the
Frameworks.props file.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Project Sdk="Microsoft.NET.Sdk"&gt;
  &lt;Import Project="Frameworks.props" /&gt;
  &lt;PropertyGroup&gt;
    &lt;TargetFrameworks&gt;$(TheFramework)&lt;/TargetFrameworks&gt;
  &lt;/PropertyGroup&gt;
&lt;/Project&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The unevaluated MSBuild property value was used and would result in the
NuGet package restore failing.</p>

<p>Now the evaluated property value is used when restoring dependencies.</p>

<p><strong>ASP.NET Core minified files and map files are no longer formatted</strong></p>

<p>On creating a new ASP.NET Core project the minified files were being
re-formatted and were no longer minified. Now the .min.css, .min.js and
.map files are excluded from being re-formatted when a new ASP.NET Core
project is created.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed failure to add a new file when the default project namespace contains only numbers</strong></p>

<p>If a project has a default namespace of &lsquo;1&rsquo; then adding a new C#
file from a template would throw a null reference
exception. The problem was that the sanitized namespace for the project&rsquo;s
default namespace was null.</p>

<p><strong>Show SDK information before dependencies are restored</strong></p>

<p>When a new .NET Core project is created the Dependencies &ndash; SDK folder
would show no items until the NuGet package restore completed. Now
the SDK dependency is shown whilst the dependencies are being restored.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed remove item not added for .xaml.cs file</strong></p>

<p>When a new content page with xaml file was
added and then removed, but not deleted,
a remove item was not added for the .xaml.cs file.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed incorrect project updates when moving a file</strong></p>

<p>Moving a Resource file from one folder to another would not update
the project file correctly. Either the project file would not be
modified or the file would be removed.</p>

<p>One problem was that on moving a clone is taken of the original item
and the associated MSBuild item was copied but was still referring
back to the original location. Another problem was that an incorrect
match was being made when looking for remove items resulting in the
wrong files being removed from the project.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed being unable to use NUnit in a .NET Core test project</strong></p>

<p>The problem was that the NUnit test provider, which supports running NUnit tests
for non .NET Core projects, was finding a PackageReference for NUnit, and then
trying to load the tests for the .NET Core project and failing. To fix this the
NUnit test provider now ignores .NET Core projects so the VS Test provider will
load the tests for the project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NuGet Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.4]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/03/10/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-4/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-10T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2018/03/10/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> Support NuGet RestoreProjectStyle MSBuild Property</li>
<li> .NET Core xUnit tests not displayed if NuGet packages not cached</li>
<li> No tests displayed when project uses a NUnit PackageReference</li>
<li> NuGet MSBuild imports not removed when migrating to project.json</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.4</a>
can be found in the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/visualstudio/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#15.6">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreProjectStyle MSBuild property</h2>

<p>If a project sets the RestoreProjectStyle property to be
PackageReference then the project will be restored as though it has
PackageReferences even if it does not have any.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;RestoreProjectStyle&gt;PackageReference&lt;/RestoreProjectStyle&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This fixes runtime problems when a project references a .NET Standard
project that has PackageReferences. Without the RestoreProjectStyle set
the assemblies from the NuGet packages are not copied to the output
directory and would have to be added to the main project.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>.NET Core xUnit tests not displayed if NuGet packages are not in local NuGet cache</strong></p>

<p>If the NuGet packages that contain the VS Test adapters were not available in
the local machine&rsquo;s NuGet package cache then
the Unit Tests window would not show any tests after the NuGet
packages were restored and the project was compiled.</p>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac would not initially find any test adapter dlls
and would not attempt to discover any tests for the project after the
NuGet packages were downloaded into the NuGet package cache.</p>

<p>Now after the NuGet package restore has completed the check for a
VS Test adapter is now re-run.</p>

<p><strong>No tests displayed when a project uses a NUnit PackageReference</strong></p>

<p>The Unit Tests window would not show any unit tests when a non .NET
Core project contained a NUnit PackageReference. Visual Studio for
Mac was looking for a PackageReference that contained &lsquo;nunit.framework&rsquo;
and was not finding the NUnit NuGet package reference.</p>

<p><strong>NuGet MSBuild imports not removed when migrating to project.json</strong></p>

<p>When a Portable Class Library project was migrated to use a project.json
file the MSBuild imports added by NuGet were not removed. These imports
are added by NuGet into the generated ProjectName.nuget.props and
ProjectName.nuget.targets files on restoring a project.json file.
Leaving the import in the project file would result in the import
being used twice. When a PCL project that used Xamarin.Forms was
migrated to project.json the project would fail to compile with the
error:</p>

<pre><code>Error XF001: Xamarin.Forms targets have been imported multiple times.
Please check your project file and remove the duplicate import(s).
</code></pre>

<p>Now on migrating to project.json the MSBuild imports added by NuGet packages
to the project are removed.</p>

<p><strong>Fix unhandled exception when searching for packages</strong></p>

<p>An unhandled exception was being logged if a package source returned
an error or the package source url was invalid. This was because a
task was not being observed when the package sources were being used.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.NET Core Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.3]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/12/18/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-3/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-18T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/12/18/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> <a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/vstest">VSTest</a> Console Runner now included with Visual Studio for Mac

<ul>
<li>Allows <a href="https://xunit.github.io">xUnit</a> tests to be supported for non .NET Core projects</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> Renamed ASP.NET Core Project Templates</li>
<li> New ASP.NET Core F# Project Templates Added</li>
<li> Support Backslash in Project Template Primary Output Path</li>
<li> Support <a href="https://github.com/NuGet/Home/wiki/%5BSpec%5D-NuGet-settings-in-MSBuild">NuGet Restore MSBuild Properties</a>

<ul>
<li>RestoreAdditionalProjectFallbackFolders</li>
<li>RestoreAdditionalProjectSources</li>
<li>RestoreFallbackFolders</li>
<li>RestorePackagesPath</li>
<li>RestoreSources</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> Fixed transitive project references not supported</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.3</a> can be found in the <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/news/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#release-date-december-4-2017---visual-studio-2017-version-73-730797">release notes</a></p>

<h2>VSTest Console Runner</h2>

<p>Previous versions of Visual Studio for Mac would use <strong>dotnet vstest</strong>,
included with the .NET Core SDK,
to run unit tests for .NET Core projects. Now Visual Studio for Mac includes
the <a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/vstest">VSTest</a> Console runner and uses that instead of using the .NET Core SDK.</p>

<p>The standalone VSTest Console runner allows other project types, not just .NET Core projects, to
be supported. Visual Studio for Mac can now run <a href="https://xunit.github.io">xUnit</a> tests
for .NET Framework projects. Previously only NUnit was supported.</p>

<p>Let us take a look at using xUnit in a .NET Framework project.</p>

<p>First create a .NET Framework Library project by opening the New Project dialog and selecting
Library from the Other &ndash; .NET &ndash; General category.</p>

<p>Install the following NuGet packages into the project.</p>

<ul>
<li>xunit</li>
<li>xunit.runner.visualstudio</li>
</ul>


<p>Edit MyClass.cs and add some xUnit tests, as shown below:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>using Xunit;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>namespace xUnitTests
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  public class MyClass
</span><span class='line'>  {
</span><span class='line'>      [Fact]
</span><span class='line'>      public void PassingTest()
</span><span class='line'>      {
</span><span class='line'>          Assert.True(true);
</span><span class='line'>      }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      [Fact]
</span><span class='line'>      public void FailingTest()
</span><span class='line'>      {
</span><span class='line'>          Assert.False(true);
</span><span class='line'>      }
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>}
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Building the project should then show the xUnit tests in the Unit Tests window.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-3/xUnitTestsInUnitTestsWindow.png" title="xUnit tests in Unit Tests window" alt="xUnit tests in Unit Tests window"></p>

<p>Note that, due to a bug in Visual Studio for Mac, the tests may not appear in the
Unit Tests window if the
xunit.runner.visualstudio was not available in the local machine&rsquo;s NuGet
package cache when it was added to the project. Closing and re-opening the
solution should allow the tests to be discovered.</p>

<p>The tests can then be run or debugged in the usual way.</p>

<p>Currently MSTest is not yet supported in .NET Framework projects. The tests are discovered
but they fail to run with an access denied error message:</p>

<pre><code>An exception occurred while invoking executor 'executor://mstestadapter/v2': 
Access to the path "/TestResults" is denied.
</code></pre>

<h2>Renamed ASP.NET Core Project Templates</h2>

<p>The ASP.NET Core template names displayed in the New Project dialog
have been changed to be more consistent with Visual Studio on Windows.</p>

<ul>
<li>&lsquo;ASP.NET Core Web App (Razor Pages)&rsquo; renamed to &lsquo;ASP.NET Core Web App&rsquo;</li>
<li>&lsquo;ASP.NET Core Web App&rsquo; renamed to &lsquo;ASP.NET Core Web App (MVC)&rsquo;</li>
</ul>


<p>Visual Studio uses (Model-View-Controller) but the shorter
MVC is used by Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<h2>New ASP.NET Core F# Project Templates Added</h2>

<p>The following ASP.NET Core F# project templates are now available from the
New Project dialog.</p>

<ul>
<li>ASP.NET Core Empty

<ul>
<li>.NET Core 1.x and 2.0</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ASP.NET Core Web API

<ul>
<li>.NET Core 2.0 only</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Support Backslash in Project Template Primary Output Path</h2>

<p>The template.json file used by the new templating engine uses a
primaryOutputs property for projects and files. If the paths used
contained backslashes then the project was not added to the
solution.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>"primaryOutputs": [
</span><span class='line'>  { "path": "Library1\\Library1.csproj" },
</span><span class='line'>  { "path": "Library2\\Library2.csproj" }
</span><span class='line'>]</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now the paths have the backslashes replaced with forward slashes if
the current platform does not support backslash as a path
separator.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreAdditionalProjectFallbackFolders MSBuild Property</h2>

<p>The RestoreAdditionalProjectFallbackFolders MSBuild property is
read and appended to the list of fallback folders stored in the
project.assets.json file. The .NET Core 2.0 SDK will set this
MSBuild property to point to the NuGet package fallback folder
that is installed with the SDK. This will be used
to resolve NuGet packages first before downloading them to the
~/.nuget/packages folder.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreAdditionalProjectSources MSBuild Property</h2>

<p>The RestoreAdditionalProjectSources MSBuild property can be used
to add additional package sources to the existing list of sources
used to resolve packages.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreFallbackFolders MSBuild Property</h2>

<p>The RestoreFallbackFolders MSBuild property can be used by project that uses
PackageReferences to define a set of package fallback folders that
will override any specified in the NuGet.Config file. It can also
be used to clear any pre-defined fallback folders by specifying
&lsquo;clear&rsquo; as its value. Note that this value does not affect any
folders defined by RestoreAdditionalProjectFallbackFolders which
will be appended even if RestoreFallbackFolders is set to &lsquo;clear&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>Support RestorePackagesPath MSBuild Property</h2>

<p>The RestorePackagesPath MSBuild property can be used to override the global packages
folder location when a project uses a PackageReference.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreSources MSBuild property</h2>

<p>The RestoreSources MSBuild property can be used to override
the sources defined by any NuGet.Config file. Any sources defined in the
RestoreAdditionalProjectSources MSBuild property will still be appended to the
list of sources if RestoreSources is defined.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Fixed Transitive Project References not supported</strong></p>

<p>With three .NET Core projects, LibC referencing LibB referencing LibA,
the types defined by LibA were not available to LibC unless it was
directly referencing LibA. In Visual Studio for Mac 7.3 the types
defined by LibA are available to LibC without LibC directly
referencing LibA.</p>

<p><strong>Portable Class Library projects can now be referenced by .NET Core projects</strong></p>

<p>Portable Class Library (PCL) projects could not be referenced by .NET Core
projects or .NET Standard projects. The Edit References dialog would show
&ldquo;Incompatible target framework&rdquo; for the PCL project when trying to add the
reference.</p>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac now has the same behaviour as Visual Studio on Windows where
a .NET Standard project can reference any PCL project.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed MSBuild Update item not removed from project</strong></p>

<p>If a file was deleted from a project, or removed without deleting,
and the file was the last file for a particular wildcard include, the
Update item for the file was not being removed from the project.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed MSBuild Remove item not added when Update item exists</strong></p>

<p>With a project that contained a single .cs file, and that file had
an Update item defined, when the file was removed from the project,
without deleting it, a Remove item was not being added to the project for the file.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed Remove item not being added when file excluded from project</strong></p>

<p>When the last file was removed from the project, but not deleted, an
MSBuild Remove item was not added to the project for the file.</p>

<ol>
<li>Create a .NET Standard 2.0 project.</li>
<li>Right click Class1.cs and select Remove.</li>
<li>Select Remove from Project in the dialog that opens.</li>
<li>Close and re-open solution.</li>
</ol>


<p>The Class1.cs file was still shown in the Solution window when it should have been
removed. The project file did not have a Compile remove item for Class1.cs when it should
have been added:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Compile Remove="Class1.cs" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Deleting a XAML file left an MSBuild Remove item in project file</strong></p>

<p>When a .xaml file in a project was deleted the associated
Remove MSBuild item, if it was present, was not being removed from the
project file.</p>

<ol>
<li> Create a new .NET Standard 2.0 project.</li>
<li> Add Xamarin.Forms 2.3 NuGet package.</li>
<li> Add a new Content Page with Xaml file using the New File dialog.</li>
<li> In the Solution window select the .xaml file and delete it.</li>
</ol>


<p>All MSBuild items associated with the .xaml file should have been
removed from the project file but instead a None item would remain.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;None Remove="MyPage.xaml" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Fix MSBuild remove item not added when adding a XAML file</strong></p>

<p>Adding a new .xaml file to a project was not adding a None Remove
item for the .xaml file to remove it from the default wildcard include for all
files.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;None Remove="MyNewPage.xaml" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>On reloading the solution the Solution window would show two .xaml
files &ndash; one EmbeddedResource item and one None item.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed MSBuild condition evaluation when using Czech locale</strong></p>

<p>With the primary operating system language set to Czech, creating a new .NET
Core project would result in the project having a target framework of net461.</p>

<p>The problem was that Single.TryParse was returing true for an empty string
when the machine&rsquo;s culture was &lsquo;cs-CZ&rsquo;. This was causing the MSBuild condition
evaluation to be treated as a boolean comparison incorrectly in some cases.
The condition below would return false even though the property was
not defined and both sides of the condition were empty strings:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;PropertyGroup Condition="'$(TargetFrameworkIdentifier)' == ''"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This was causing the TargetFrameworkIdentifier to not be set for
.NET Core projects so the default of .NETFramework was being used.</p>

<p><strong>Re-evaluate AppliesTo condition on capability change</strong></p>

<p>Fixed the AppliesTo attribute not attaching a project extension to
a project after a NuGet package restore enabled a project capability.
The AppliesTo attribute allows a project extension to be associated
to a project based on its capabilities.</p>

<p>If the project extension uses an AppliesTo attribute which is
initially false and then a new project capability is added, and the
project is re-evaluated, the AppliesTo attribute is now
re-evaluated. This will then cause the project extension to be
attached to the project. If the project extension was attached to the
project and the project capability is removed then the project
extension will now be removed when the project is re-evaluated.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed being unable to run a new Azure Functions project</strong></p>

<p>Creating a new Azure Functions project would result in
being unable to run the project until the solution was closed
and re-opened again. After the NuGet packages are restored the
project can be run but this information was not updated in Visual Studio
for Mac.</p>

<p>Now after a NuGet package restore, when re-evaluating the project,
the solution startup item is updated if there is no startup item
already defined.</p>

<p>When the project capability is removed, due to a NuGet package
being uninstalled, and the
project can no longer be run the startup item will be updated if
it was previously set to be this project.</p>

<p><strong>Fix generated NuGet files being imported twice</strong></p>

<p>The ProjectName.nuget.g.targets and ProjectName.nuget.g.props,
that are generated for .NET Core projects in the base intermediate
directory, were being imported twice.
Once by Microsoft.Common.props, that is provided with Mono, and once
again by Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<p>Importing these files twice was causing a duplicate file to be added to
the project information held in memory by Visual Studio for Mac
when Xamarin.Forms 2.4 was used and no .NET Core SDK was installed.
This would result in the content page xaml and associated C# file not
being nested in the solution window.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed items added to project when a new content page with XAML was created</strong></p>

<p>Adding a new Xamarin.Forms content page with XAML would add an
update item for the .xaml.cs file, a remove item for the xaml file,
and an include item for the xaml file.</p>

<p>An example is Xamarin.Forms 2.4 which defines wildcard includes:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;None Remove="**\*.xaml" /&gt;
&lt;EmbeddedResource Include="**\*.xaml" SubType="Designer" Generator="MSBuild:UpdateDesignTimeXaml" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Which would cause a new .xaml file added to the project and saved
in the project file as well as a remove for the None item even though
the .xaml file was already removed from the None items.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;None Remove="MyView.xaml" /&gt;

&lt;EmbeddedResource Include="MyView.xaml"&gt;
  &lt;Generator&gt;MSBuild:UpdateDesignTimeXaml"&lt;/Generator&gt;
&lt;/EmbeddedResource&gt;
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Fix DependentUpon property being saved in project</strong></p>

<p>Xamarin.Forms 2.4 defines an update item similar to:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Compile Update="**\*.xaml.cs" DependentUpon="%(Filename)" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>When a project was saved a Compile item was added to the main project
with the filename stored in the DependentUpon element. Now
the evaluated DependentUpon value is treated as being the default
value so it is not added to the project file.</p>

<p><strong>Fix xaml.cs files not being nested</strong></p>

<p>Xamarin.Forms 2.4 defines an update item similar to:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Compile Update="**\*.xaml.cs" DependentUpon="%(Filename)" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The DependentUpon property was being evaluated as &lsquo;*.xaml.cs&rsquo;.
This was causing .xaml.cs files to not be nested in the Solution window.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed build error when Xamarin.Forms 2.4 used in a .NET Standard project</strong></p>

<p>If a Xamarin.Forms .NET Standard project had a
.xaml file and a .xaml.cs file then the xaml.g.cs file would not be
generated when the project file contained no files. The
default items defined by the Xamarin.Forms NuGet package were not
being imported. This then caused a build error about the
InitializeComponent method not being defined.</p>

<p>Xamarin.Forms 2.4.0 uses default
item imports which were not being included since they are conditionally
imported and the MSBuildSDKsPath was not defined:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Import Project="$(MSBuildThisFileDirectory)Xamarin.Forms.DefaultItems.props" Condition="'$(MSBuildSDKsPath)'!=''" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>MSBuild on the command line defines the MSBuildSDKsPath globally in
its MSBuild.dll.config file. The MSBuild engine host, used when
building a project in Visual Studio for Mac, now also defines the
MSBuildSDKsPath property.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed remove item added when removing a linked file</strong></p>

<p>Deleting a file link in a .NET Core project would add a remove item
for the file instead of removing the link from the project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NuGet Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.3]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/12/10/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-3/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-10T11:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/12/10/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> Support installing System.ValueTuple NuGet Package from Quick Fixes</li>
<li> NuGetizer 3000 &ndash; Update NuGet.Build.Packaging to version 0.2</li>
<li> Support NuGet Restore MSBuild Properties

<ul>
<li>RestoreAdditionalProjectFallbackFolders</li>
<li>RestoreAdditionalProjectSources</li>
<li>RestoreFallbackFolders</li>
<li>RestorePackagesPath</li>
<li>RestoreSources</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> Fixed transitive dependencies not available when using project.json</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.3</a> can be found in the <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/news/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#release-date-december-4-2017---visual-studio-2017-version-73-730797">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>Quick Fix &ndash; Install System.ValueTuple NuGet Package</h2>

<p><a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2016/08/24/whats-new-in-csharp-7-0/">C# 7.0 introduced tuple types</a>
that may require the System.ValueTuple NuGet package
to be added to the project. Visual Studio for Mac
now offers to install the System.ValueTuple NuGet package if the project requires this NuGet package.</p>

<p>Creating a .NET Framework 4.6 project with the following code:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>public (string, int) GetValues(string id)
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  return ("Name", 25);
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>You will see error markers in the text editor. If you hover over
one of these error markers you will see a
<strong>Predefined type &lsquo;System.ValueTuple`2&rsquo; is not defined or imported</strong> message.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-3/ValueTupleTextEditorErrorTooltip.png" title="ValueTuple type not defined text editor error tooltip" alt="ValueTuple type not defined text editor error tooltip"></p>

<p>If you right click the error marker there is now a new
<strong>Install Package &lsquo;System.ValueTuple&rsquo;</strong> Quick Fix action available.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-3/TextEditorInstallSystemValueTuplePackageQuickFix.png" title="Text editor Install System.ValueTuple Package quick fix menu item" alt="Text editor Install System.ValueTuple Package quick fix menu item"></p>

<p>From this menu you can install the latest System.ValueTuple NuGet package
or open the Add Packages dialog to search for a specific version of the System.ValueTuple NuGet
package.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-3/TextEditorInstallLatestSystemValueTupleQuickFix.png" title="Text editor install latest System.ValueTuple package quick fix menu item" alt="Text editor install latest System.ValueTuple package quick fix menu item"></p>

<p>Note that if the project is targeting .NET Framework 4.7 or .NET Standard 2.0 then the
System.ValueTuple NuGet package is not required.</p>

<p>Also note that the official nuget.org package source needs to be available
for this feature to work.</p>

<h2>NuGetizer 3000 &ndash; Updated NuGet.Build.Packaging to version 0.2</h2>

<p>The version of the NuGet.Build.Packaging NuGet package used by default for NuGetizer 3000 support
has been updated from 0.1.276 to 0.2.0. This fixes a
potential build error when building with Mono 5.6.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>Using "ReportAssetsLogMessages" task from assembly "/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/2.0.0/Sdks/Microsoft.NET.Sdk/build/../tools/net46/Microsoft.NET.Build.Tasks.dll".
</span><span class='line'>Task "ReportAssetsLogMessages"
</span><span class='line'>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/2.0.0/Sdks/Microsoft.NET.Sdk/build/Microsoft.PackageDependencyResolution.targets(323,5): error MSB4018: The "ReportAssetsLogMessages" task failed unexpectedly. [RefactoringEssentials/RefactoringEssentials.2017/RefactoringEssentials.csproj]
</span><span class='line'>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/2.0.0/Sdks/Microsoft.NET.Sdk/build/Microsoft.PackageDependencyResolution.targets(323,5): error MSB4018: System.TypeLoadException: Could not resolve type with token 0100005b (from typeref, class/assembly NuGet.ProjectModel.IAssetsLogMessage, NuGet.ProjectModel, Version=4.3.0.5, Culture=neutral, PublicKeyToken=31bf3856ad364e35) [RefactoringEssentials/RefactoringEssentials.2017/RefactoringEssentials.csproj]
</span><span class='line'>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/2.0.0/Sdks/Microsoft.NET.Sdk/build/Microsoft.PackageDependencyResolution.targets(323,5): error MSB4018: at Microsoft.NET.Build.Tasks.TaskBase.Execute () [0x00000] in &lt;01420900fd004c128de2d2ee31bad624&gt;:0 [RefactoringEssentials/RefactoringEssentials.2017/RefactoringEssentials.csproj]
</span><span class='line'>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/2.0.0/Sdks/Microsoft.NET.Sdk/build/Microsoft.PackageDependencyResolution.targets(323,5): error MSB4018: at Microsoft.Build.BackEnd.TaskExecutionHost.Microsoft.Build.BackEnd.ITaskExecutionHost.Execute () [0x00023] in &lt;765502eb2f884ce79731edeb4b0517fb&gt;:0 [RefactoringEssentials/RefactoringEssentials.2017/RefactoringEssentials.csproj]
</span><span class='line'>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/2.0.0/Sdks/Microsoft.NET.Sdk/build/Microsoft.PackageDependencyResolution.targets(323,5): error MSB4018: at Microsoft.Build.BackEnd.TaskBuilder+d__26.MoveNext () [0x0022d] in &lt;765502eb2f884ce79731edeb4b0517fb&gt;:0 [RefactoringEssentials/RefactoringEssentials.2017/RefactoringEssentials.csproj]</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The ReadLegacyDependencies target from NuGet.Build.Packaging.Tasks is called when PackOnBuild
is set to true.</p>

<p>The NuGet.Build.Packaging.Tasks assembly was loading an embedded NuGet.ProjectModel
assembly that conflicts with the version that is used by Microsoft.NET.Build.Tasks.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreAdditionalProjectFallbackFolders MSBuild Property</h2>

<p>The RestoreAdditionalProjectFallbackFolders MSBuild property is
read and appended to the list of fallback folders stored in the
project.assets.json file. The .NET Core 2.0 SDK will set this
MSBuild property to point to the NuGet package fallback folder
that is installed with the SDK. This will be used
to resolve NuGet packages first before downloading them to the
~/.nuget/packages folder.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreAdditionalProjectSources MSBuild Property</h2>

<p>The RestoreAdditionalProjectSources MSBuild property can be used
to add additional package sources to the existing list of sources
used to resolve packages.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreFallbackFolders MSBuild Property</h2>

<p>The RestoreFallbackFolders MSBuild property can be used by project that uses
PackageReferences to define a set of package fallback folders that
will override any specified in the NuGet.Config file. It can also
be used to clear any pre-defined fallback folders by specifying
&lsquo;clear&rsquo; as its value. Note that this value does not affect any
folders defined by RestoreAdditionalProjectFallbackFolders which
will be appended even if RestoreFallbackFolders is set to &lsquo;clear&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>Support RestorePackagesPath MSBuild Property</h2>

<p>The RestorePackagesPath MSBuild property can be used to override the global packages
folder location when a project uses a PackageReference.</p>

<h2>Support RestoreSources MSBuild property</h2>

<p>The RestoreSources MSBuild property can be used to override
the sources defined by any NuGet.Config file. Any sources defined in the
RestoreAdditionalProjectSources MSBuild property will still be appended to the
list of sources if RestoreSources is defined.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Transitive dependencies not available when using project.json</strong></p>

<p>With two projects A and B that both use project.json files, project B
referencing project A, the NuGet package dependencies used by project
A were not available to project B transitively. This was because the
project reference information was not being used
when a restore occurred. This caused the assemblies from the transitively
referenced NuGet packages to not be added to the
project.lock.json file for Project B.</p>

<p><strong>Unable to debug a new Azure Functions project without re-opening project</strong></p>

<p>After creating a new Azure Functions project it was possible to build the
project but not to debug it or run it. On closing and re-opening the solution
it would be possible to debug and run the Azure Functions project.</p>

<p>When Visual Studio for Mac created a new Azure Functions project
it initially determined that it could not run or debug the project.
After the Azure Functions project has its PackageReferences restored
it gains an AzureFunctions project capability. This capability is used to
determine if the project can be run. This change in the capability
was not handled by Visual Studio for Mac so it did not allow the
project to be run until the project was closed and re-opened.</p>

<p>Now, after the NuGet package restore is finished, the project is
re-evaluated and a check is made to see if the project can now be run.</p>

<p><strong>Fix generated NuGet files being imported twice</strong></p>

<p>The generated ProjectName.nuget.g.targets and ProjectName.nuget.g.props
that are created for .NET Core projects in the base intermediate
directory were being imported twice when evaluating the project.
Once by Microsoft.Common.props, provided with Mono, and once
by Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<p>This duplicate import was resulting in a duplicate file being added
to the project held in memory by Visual Studio for Mac when the
Xamarin.Forms 2.4 NuGet package was used in a .NET Standard
project and no .NET Core SDK is installed. This would result in the
content page xaml and associated C# file not being nested in the
solution window.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Template Creator for Visual Studio for Mac]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/11/12/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-12T14:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/11/12/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-template-creator-addin">Template Creator extension</a> provides a way to create a project template from an existing project
or solution open in Visual Studio for Mac and have the project template available in the New
Project dialog straight away.</p>

<p>The Template Creator uses the <a href="https://github.com/dotnet/templating">.NET Core templating engine</a>
to create the projects from the project templates.</p>

<p>Let us take a look in more detail at what the Template Creator extension provides in Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<h2>Features</h2>

<ul>
<li> Create a project template from an existing solution or project</li>
<li> Create custom top level project template categories</li>
</ul>


<h2>Supports</h2>

<ul>
<li>Visual Studio Mac 7.0 or later.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Creating a new Project Template</h2>

<p>To create a new project template for a project opened in Visual Studio for Mac,
right click the project and select Create Template.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/ProjectCreateTemplateMenu.png" title="Project - Create Template context menu" alt="Project - Create Template context menu"></p>

<p>A Template Information dialog is then opened.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/TemplateInformationDialog.png" title="Template Information dialog" alt="Template Information dialog"></p>

<p>The information in the dialog is used to populate the generated template.json file. Further
details on what the template.json file holds is available in the <a href="https://github.com/dotnet/templating/wiki/Reference-for-template.json">reference for template.json</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Author

<ul>
<li>Author of the project template.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Display Name

<ul>
<li>This is the template name displayed in the New Project dialog.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Description

<ul>
<li>This is the description displayed in the New Project dialog.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Category

<ul>
<li>This is the category in the New Project dialog used by the template.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Short Name

<ul>
<li>This is the short name for the template that can be used from the .NET Core command line.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Default Project Name

<ul>
<li>This is the default project name that will be used with the .NET Core command line.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Identity

<ul>
<li>This is the unique id for the template. This should be unique across all custom
project templates.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Group Identity

<ul>
<li>This is typically a substring of the template&rsquo;s Identity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>By default the project template will use the Other &ndash; .NET &ndash; General category in the
New Project dialog. To change the category click the browse button next to the category text
box to open the Template Categories dialog.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/TemplateCategoriesDialog.png" title="Template Categories dialog" alt="Template Categories dialog"></p>

<p>Select the required category and click OK. The selected category will then be updated
in the Template Information dialog.</p>

<p>Click OK to generate the template.json file. The template.json file will be opened
in the text editor. It will also be displayed in the Solution window in the
.template.config folder.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/ProjectTemplateJsonFile.png" title="template.json file created for project" alt="template.json file created for project"></p>

<p>The project template is now available in the New Project dialog.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/CustomProjectTemplateInNewProjectDialog.png" title="Custom project template in New Project dialog" alt="Custom template in New Project dialog"></p>

<h2>Updating a Project Template</h2>

<p>After the project template is created you can modify the original project and its
template.json file as required.</p>

<p>Changes made to the project are available in the New Project dialog immediately.</p>

<p>Changes made to the template.json file are available immediately in the same
instance of Visual Studio for Mac where the template.json file is being edited.</p>

<h2>Multiple Projects in a Template</h2>

<p>A project template may create more than one project. To create a project template
for all projects in the solution right click the solution and select Create Template.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/SolutionCreateTemplateMenu.png" title="Solution - Create Template context menu" alt="Solution - Create Template context menu"></p>

<p>A template.json file will be created in a .template.config directory inside the solution&rsquo;s
directory.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/TwoProjectsTemplateJsonFile.png" title="template.json file created for soluton" alt="template.json file created for solution"></p>

<p>Note that in order for the new projects created to use the name specified in the New Project
dialog they should all have a common start to their name. The template.json file&rsquo;s <code>sourceName</code>
will be the part that is replaced with the name of the project specified in the New Project dialog.</p>

<h2>Configuring Registered Project Templates</h2>

<p>The .NET Core templating engine supports project templates in NuGet packages or project templates
that unpackaged in a directory. The Template Creator extension does
not package the project templates into a NuGet package and instead stores a set of directories that
are scanned by the .NET Core templating engine for templates. The set of directories that are
registered can be viewed and updated in the Preferences dialog from the Templates &ndash; Custom Folders section.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/PreferencesCustomFolders.png" title="Preferences dialog - Templates - Custom Folders" alt="Preferences dialog - Templates - Custom Folders"></p>

<p>The templating engine will scan the configured directories and look for all the template.json files
which define the project templates. The project templates found are then made available to the
Visual Studio for Mac&rsquo;s New Project dialog by the Template Creator extension.</p>

<p>When the template.json file is created using the information in the Template Information dialog
the Template Creator extenxion also registers the
project&rsquo;s directory so it will be scanned by the templating engine.</p>

<p>To remove a project
template from the New Project dialog you can either delete the template.json file or
remove the folder from the Custom Folders defined in the Preferences dialog.</p>

<p>If you have an existing set of project templates that use template.json files and are not
in a NuGet package then you can register a single parent directory in the Preferences dialog.</p>

<h2>Custom Categories</h2>

<p>Custom top level categories can be defined for your project templates by adding them in
Preferences &ndash; Templates &ndash; Custom Categories.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/PreferencesCustomCategories.png" title="Preferences dialog - Templates - Custom Categories" alt="Preferences dialog - Templates - Custom Categories"></p>

<p>The Add Top Level Category button will add a new top level category and two child category
levels. The New Project dialog requires three category levels. The ids used should ensure that
the full path to the template&rsquo;s category is unique. For example, with a custom category
<code>custom/net/general</code> there should not be another top level <code>custom</code> category id, but the second
and third level category ids can be re-used in another top level category, such as <code>top/net/general</code>.</p>

<p>The Add Category button will add a single child category to the currently selected category
whilst the Remove button will remove the selected category.</p>

<p>Note that changes to the categories require Visual Studio for Mac to be restarted before they
are visible in the New Project dialog.</p>

<p>Also note that it is not currently possible to extend existing project template categories
using the Template Creator extension.</p>

<h2>Diagnosing Template Problems</h2>

<p>If the template does not appear in the New Project dialog or fails to be created then
you may be able to diagnose the problem by opening the Templating Log window. This is
available from the View &ndash; Pads menu.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/MainMenuViewPadsTemplatingLog.png" title="Main menu - View - Pads - Templating Log" alt="Main menu - View - Templating Log"></p>

<p>This window will show messages returned from the .NET Core templating engine and any errors
reported by the Template Creator extension.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/TemplateCreatorForVisualStudioMac/TemplatingLogWindow.png" title="Templating Log window" alt="Templating Log window"></p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>The Template Creator extension is available to download from <a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-template-creator-addin/releases/download/0.1/MonoDevelop.TemplateCreator_0.1.mpack">GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>To install the extension open the Extensions Manager by selecting Extensions&hellip; from the main menu. Click the Install from file button. Select the .mpack file and then click the Open button.</p>

<p>The extension is also available in the Extensions Manager from the
<a href="http://addins.monodevelop.com/Project/Index/305">Visual Studio Extension Repository (Beta channel)</a>.</p>

<h2>Source Code</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-template-creator-addin">Template Creator extension for Visual Studio for Mac and MonoDevelop</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Further Reading</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2017/04/02/how-to-create-your-own-templates-for-dotnet-new/">How to create your own templates for dotnet new</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dotnet/templating/wiki/Reference-for-template.json">Reference for template.json</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.jimbobbennett.io/creating-visual-studio-project-and-solution-templates-part-3-vs-for-mac-extension/">Creating Visual Studio project and solution templates &ndash; Part 3, VS for Mac extension</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ligershark/sidewafflev2">SideWaffle v2 for Visual Studio</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.NET Core Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.2]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/11/08/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-2/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-08T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/11/08/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> Support NuGet package fallback folders</li>
<li> Support AssetTargetFallback</li>
<li> Xamarin.Forms 2.4 support (VS for Mac 7.2.2)</li>
<li> Fixed transitive types from references not being available</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.2</a> can be found in the <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/news/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#release-date-october-9-2017---visual-studio-2017-for-mac-720636">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>NuGet package fallback folders support</h2>

<p>The .NET Core SDK 2.0 defines a NuGet package fallback folder <code>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/NuGetFallbackFolder</code> that can be used when looking
for NuGet packages whilst restoring. This fallback folder is now supported by
Visual Studio for Mac 7.2 so that on restoring a .NET Core 2.0 project the NuGet
packages from the fallback folder will be found and do not need to be downloaded from nuget.org into the
local machine NuGet package cache <code>~/.nuget/packages</code>. This should speed up NuGet package restore for .NET Core 2.0 and .NET Standard 2.0 projects the first time it occurs.</p>

<p>As well as the NuGet fallback folders Visual Studio for Mac will now add the following items to the generated project.assets.json
if they are available:</p>

<ul>
<li>configFilePaths</li>
<li>sources</li>
<li>warningProperties</li>
</ul>


<h2>AssetTargetFallback support</h2>

<p>The .NET Core 2.0 SDK uses an AssetTargetFallback MSBuild property
defined in an imported SDK MSBuild files. This is used instead
of the PackageTargetFallback property when determining if a NuGet
package is compatible. Currently the AssetTargetFallback property
is set to net461 by the .NET Core 2.0 SDK which allows .NET Core projects to use NuGet
packages that include assemblies that target the full .NET Framework.
The supported fallback frameworks are now added to the generated
project.assets.json file by Visual Studio for Mac when a .NET Core 2.0 project is restored.</p>

<h2>NuGet package restore now fails if package and asset target fallbacks are defined by a project</h2>

<p>If both AssetTargetFallback and PackageTargetFallback are defined by a project then the
NuGet restore will fail with an error indicating that they cannot
be used together. This mirrors the behaviour of the .NET Core command
line restore.</p>

<h2>Mark implicit PackageReferences as auto referenced</h2>

<p>PackageReference items that have IsImplicitlyDefined set to true
in their metadata now have autoRefererenced set to true in the project.assets.json file.</p>

<h2>Support parsing MSBuild conditions with unquoted properties</h2>

<p>The .NET Core 2.0 SDK uses conditions that pass properties to the
Exists function without using single quotes around the MSBuild property.
This is now supported by Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;PropertyGroup Condition="Exists($(FileName))"&gt;
</code></pre>

<h2>Xamarin.Forms 2.4 support</h2>

<p>The following sections cover bug fixes made in Visual Studio for Mac 7.2.2
to improve support for <a href="https://developer.xamarin.com/releases/xamarin-forms/xamarin-forms-2.4/2.4.0-stable/">Xamarin.Forms 2.4</a> and later versions. Xamarin.Forms 2.4 includes .NET Standard support as well as defining default MSBuild items for
.NET Core and .NET Standard projects. These default MSBuild items were not
handled by Visual Studio for Mac 7.2.0 and earlier versions. The main symptoms of Visual Studio for Mac not supporting Xamarin.Forms 2.4 were:</p>

<ul>
<li>Duplicate .xaml files in the Solution window.</li>
<li>Nesting of .xaml and .xaml.cs files not working in Solution window.</li>
<li>MSBuild items incorrectly added to SDK style projects.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Generated NuGet files being imported twice</h3>

<p>The generated NuGet files, .nuget.g.targets and .nuget.g.props,
that are created for .NET Core projects were being imported twice.
Once by Microsoft.Common.props, that is provided with Mono, and once
by Visual Studio for Mac.</p>

<p>This double import was causing a duplicate file
to be added to the
project when Xamarin.Forms 2.4
was used in a .NET Standard project and the .NET Core SDK was not
installed. This would result in the .xaml file and associated
.xaml.cs file not being nested in the solution window.</p>

<h3>MSBuild items added when new xaml file added to project</h3>

<p>Adding a new Xamarin.Forms content page with XAML would incorrectly add an
update item to the project for the .xaml.cs file when an SDK style project
was used.</p>

<p>When a new .xaml file was added to an SDK style project a None item as well as an EmbeddedResource item would incorrectly be added to the project file.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;None Remove="MyView.xaml" /&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;EmbeddedResource Include="MyView.xaml"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;Generator&gt;MSBuild:UpdateDesignTimeXaml"&lt;/Generator&gt;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/EmbeddedResource&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Compile item added with DependentUpon metadata</h3>

<p>Xamarin.Forms 2.4 defines a wildcard update similar to:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Compile Update="**\*.xaml.cs" DependentUpon="%(Filename)" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>When a project was saved in Visual Studio for Mac a Compile item was
incorrectly added to the main project with the evaluated value stored in the
DependentUpon element.</p>

<h3>DependentUpon being evaluated incorrectly</h3>

<p>Metadata defined for wildcard MSBuild items were being evaluated using
the wildcard item instead of the expanded item. This
was causing .xaml.cs files to not be nested in the Solution window
for Xamarin.Forms 2.4.</p>

<p>Xamarin.Forms 2.4 defines an update item similar to:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Compile Update="**\*.xaml.cs" DependentUpon="%(Filename)" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The DependentUpon property was evaluated using the wildcard item
which resulted in the DependentUpon property being
evaluated as &lsquo;*.xaml.cs&rsquo; instead of the filename of the item that was
updated by the wildcard.</p>

<h3>Define MSBuildSDKsPath for MSBuild engine host</h3>

<p>MSBuild when run on the command line defines the MSBuildSDKsPath in
its MSBuild.dll.config file. The MSBuild engine host that is used
when building with Visual Studio for Mac now also defines the MSBuildSDKsPath property. Previously this was not being defined.</p>

<p>This fixes a build error when using Xamarin.Forms 2.4.0 in an SDK style
project that targets .NET Standard. Xamarin.Forms 2.4.0 uses default
item imports which were not being included since they are conditionally
imported based on the MSBuildSDKsPath property value:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Import Project="$(MSBuildThisFileDirectory)Xamarin.Forms.DefaultItems.props" 
    Condition="'$(MSBuildSDKsPath)'!=''" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>If the SDK style project had a .xaml file and a .xaml.cs file then
the .xaml.g.cs file was not being generated when the project had no files
explicitly defined in the project file. This
then caused a build error about the InitializeComponent method not
being defined.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Fixed transitive assembly references not available until restart</strong></p>

<p>Given a solution that contains three .NET Standard projects: LibC
references LibB which references LibA. If the Newtonsoft.Json NuGet
package was installed into LibA the types from this NuGet package
were not available in LibB or LibC until the solution was closed and
re-opened again. Closing and re-opening the solution refreshes the
reference information used by the type system. Now when a NuGet
package is installed into a .NET Core project the projects that
reference this project have their reference information refreshed. Types from
the installed NuGet packages are then available in projects that
reference this updated project either directly or indirectly.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed transitive project references after editing a project file</strong></p>

<p>Given a solution that contains three .NET Standard projects: LibC references
LibB which references LibA. If a NuGet package is added to LibA by
editing its project file in the text editor the types from this NuGet
package were not available to LibB or LibC without restarting Visual Studio
for Mac or until the packages were restored for the solution. Now when the project file
is saved the projects that directly or indirectly reference the project
will be restored.</p>

<p><strong>Ignore project references with ReferenceOutputAssembly set to false when restoring</strong></p>

<p>Project references that have ReferenceOutputAssembly are now not
added to the project.assets.json file. This was causing
the NuGet package restore to fail in some cases. For example, if a .NET Standard
project has a project reference to a .NET Core App project, but has the
ReferenceOutputAssembly set to false, then running dotnet restore from the
command line would work, but the restore would fail in Visual Studio for Mac.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NuGet Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.2]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/10/28/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-2/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-28T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/10/28/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li> NuGet 4.3.1 support</li>
<li> NuGet fallback folders support</li>
<li> AssetTargetFallback support</li>
<li> NuGet operations can be cancelled on closing the solution</li>
<li> Fixed transitive types from references not being available</li>
<li> Fixed credential dialog being shown multiple times on opening a solution</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.2</a> can be found in the <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/news/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#release-date-october-9-2017---visual-studio-2017-for-mac-720636">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>NuGet 4.3.1 support</h2>

<p>NuGet 4.3.1.4445 is now included with Visual Studio for Mac 7.2.</p>

<p>NuGet 4.3.1 includes <a href="https://github.com/NuGet/Home/issues/5806">a fix for imports in the project.json file being ignored</a> which could cause a NuGet package
to incorrectly be considered incompatible when restoring NuGet packages.</p>

<h2>NuGet package fallback folders support</h2>

<p>The .NET Core SDK 2.0 defines a NuGet package fallback folder <code>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk/NuGetFallbackFolder</code> that can be used when looking
for NuGet packages whilst restoring. This fallback folder is now supported by
Visual Studio for Mac 7.2 so that on restoring a .NET Core 2.0 project the NuGet
packages from the fallback folder will be found and do not need to be downloaded from nuget.org into the
local machine NuGet package cache <code>~/.nuget/packages</code>. This should speed up NuGet package restore for .NET Core 2.0 and .NET Standard 2.0 projects the first time it occurs.</p>

<p>As well as the NuGet fallback folders Visual Studio for Mac will now add the following items to the generated project.assets.json
if they are available:</p>

<ul>
<li>configFilePaths</li>
<li>sources</li>
<li>warningProperties</li>
</ul>


<h2>AssetTargetFallback support</h2>

<p>The .NET Core 2.0 SDK uses an AssetTargetFallback MSBuild property
defined in an imported SDK MSBuild files. This is used instead
of the PackageTargetFallback property when determining if a NuGet
package is compatible. Currently the AssetTargetFallback property
is set to net461 by the .NET Core 2.0 SDK which allows .NET Core projects to use NuGet
packages that include assemblies that target the full .NET Framework.
The supported fallback frameworks are now added to the generated
project.assets.json file by Visual Studio for Mac when a .NET Core 2.0 project is restored.</p>

<h2>NuGet operations can be cancelled on the closing the solution</h2>

<p>Previously when closing the solution, or closing Visual Studio for Mac, when a NuGet package
operation was still running would result in a dialog being displayed saying that the
solution cannot be closed until the NuGet operation was completed.
NuGet v3 and above now allow the NuGet
operations to be cancelled so now the dialog allows the current
operation to be cancelled. If the
operation is taking a while to cancel a busy spinner image will be displayed in
the dialog.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-2/CancelNuGetOperationOnClosingSolutionDialog.png" title="Cancel NuGet operation dialog on closing solution" alt="Cancel NuGet operation dialog on closing solution"></p>

<p>If a restore is being run when the solution
will be closed the restore will be cancelled automatically without showing the dialog.</p>

<h2>NuGet package restore now fails if package and asset target fallbacks are defined by a project</h2>

<p>If both AssetTargetFallback and PackageTargetFallback are defined by a project then the
NuGet restore will fail with an error indicating that they cannot
be used together. This mirrors the behaviour of the .NET Core command
line restore.</p>

<h2>Support imported package references in non .NET Core projects</h2>

<p>If a non .NET Core project had no PackageReference items but imported a file that
did have PackageReference items the NuGet packages were not restored
on opening the solution. This was because only the PackageReference
items defined directly in the project were checked to determine if the
project used NuGet packages. Now the evaluated MSBuild items are checked
so any imported PackageReference items are detected and a restore
will be run on opening the solution.</p>

<p>Note that imported PackageReference items are not displayed in the
Packages folder.</p>

<h2>Package Console is no longer opened when a NuGet operation is cancelled</h2>

<p>When a NuGet operation is cancelled from the main status bar the
Package Console is now not opened when the NuGet operation fails due
to the cancellation. If the NuGet operation is not cancelled then the
Package Console window will still be opened as before if the operation fails.
This is also a workaround for Visual Studio for Mac closing the currently displayed
dialog when the Package Console window opens after the NuGet operation
is cancelled when closing the solution.</p>

<h2>Whitespace is now trimmed when creating a new package source</h2>

<p>When creating a new package source copying and pasting NuGet package source url can sometimes copy extra
whitespace which can then result in NuGet package restore errors such as:</p>

<pre><code>Failed to verify the root directory of local source
' https://api.nuget.org/v3/index.json'.
</code></pre>

<p>The package source name and url will now have whitespace trimmed to avoid
this copy and paste problem. This also
matches Visual Studio on Windows behaviour.</p>

<h2>Mark implicit PackageReferences as auto referenced</h2>

<p>PackageReference items that have IsImplicitlyDefined set to true
in their metadata now have autoRefererenced set to true in the project.assets.json file.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Fixed transitive assembly references not available until restart</strong></p>

<p>Given a solution that contains three .NET Standard projects: LibC
references LibB which references LibA. If the Newtonsoft.Json NuGet
package was installed into LibA the types from this NuGet package
were not available in LibB or LibC until the solution was closed and
re-opened again. Closing and re-opening the solution refreshes the
reference information used by the type system. Now when a NuGet
package is installed into a .NET Core project the projects that
reference this project have their reference information refreshed. Types from
the installed NuGet packages are then available in projects that
reference this updated project either directly or indirectly.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed transitive project references after editing a project file</strong></p>

<p>Given a solution that contains three .NET Standard projects: LibC references
LibB which references LibA. If a NuGet package is added to LibA by
editing its project file in the text editor the types from this NuGet
package were not available to LibB or LibC without restarting Visual Studio
for Mac or until the packages were restored for the solution. Now when the project file
is saved the projects that directly or indirectly reference the project
will be restored.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed credential dialog shown multiple times on opening a solution</strong></p>

<p>With check for updates enabled, multiple projects in the solution,
and a package source that was missing or had invalid credentials,
on opening the solution the credential dialog would be displayed multiple
times even if the correct username and password was entered or the
dialog was cancelled. The dialog was being displayed for each
project and the credential information was not being re-used.</p>

<p>Now the NuGet source repositories are re-used when checking
for updates and also when restoring the projects when the solution
is first opened. Any valid credentials entered will be re-used
when checking the remaining projects. If the credential dialog is
cancelled then the dialog is no longer displayed again whilst
checking for updates for the other projects.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed credential dialog displayed when credentials are available</strong></p>

<p>With valid credentials stored in the Mac key chain the credential dialog would
still be displayed when it should not have been. The problem was that the
NuGet credential service puts itself in a retry mode if any of the
credential providers are used when trying to authenticate against a
package source. Once in this retry mode the Visual Studio for Mac credential
provider would always show a dialog asking for the credentials instead
of re-using the existing credentials. To avoid this the credential
service is reset before any user actions, such as opening the Add Packages
dialog, running a restore or an update.</p>

<p><strong>Fixed crash when displaying Chinese characters in the Add Packages dialog</strong></p>

<p>With the NuGet v3 package source <a href="https://api.nuget.org/v3/index.json">https://api.nuget.org/v3/index.json</a>
selected, searching for Microsoft.AspNet.WebApi.Client would result in
the Visual Studio for Mac terminating when an attempt was made to display the results
in the Add Packages dialog.
The crash was in the Pango library when it attempted to determine the size of
the package title displayed in the search results. If the package
title contained Chinese characters then Pango would throw an exception:</p>

<pre><code>Illegal byte sequence encounted in the input.
at (wrapper managed-to-native) Pango.Layout:pango_layout_get_pixel_size (intptr,int&amp;,int&amp;)
</code></pre>

<p>Then when Visual Studio for Mac tried to use Pango again to determine the
size of the text this would result in Visual Studio for Mac terminating.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>Pango-WARNING (recursed) **: shaping failure, expect ugly output.
</span><span class='line'>shape-engine='BasicEngineCoreText', font='.SF NS Text',
</span><span class='line'>text=''Stacktrace:
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  at &lt;unknown&gt; &lt;0xffffffff&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  at (wrapper managed-to-native) Pango.Layout.pango_layout_get_pixel_size (intptr,int&,int&) [0x0000b] in &lt;c7aa2d93df4045df8dc71d5439f99d72&gt;:0</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If the NuGet v2 package source was used then this crash did not occur
since the package title was not returned in the search results and the package id would be
displayed instead which does not contain Chinese characters.</p>

<p>As a workaround the Add Packages dialog now displays the package id
instead of the package title.</p>

<p><strong>Ignore project references with ReferenceOutputAssembly set to false when restoring</strong></p>

<p>Project references that have ReferenceOutputAssembly are now not
added to the project.assets.json file. This was causing
the NuGet package restore to fail in some cases. For example, if a .NET Standard
project has a project reference to a .NET Core App project, but has the
ReferenceOutputAssembly set to false, then running dotnet restore from the
command line would work, but the restore would fail in Visual Studio for Mac.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NuGet Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/08/26/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-1/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-26T14:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/08/26/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>New Features</h2>

<ul>
<li> NuGet 4.3 support</li>
<li> Support PackageReference in non .NET Core projects</li>
<li> Enable file template when a NuGet package is installed</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.1</a> can be found in the <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/news/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#release-date-august-14-2017---visual-studio-for-mac-7101297">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>NuGet 4.3 Support</h2>

<p>NuGet 4.3.0.2418 is now included with Visual Studio for Mac 7.1.</p>

<p>This version of NuGet adds support for .NET Core 2.0 and .NET Standard 2.0
target frameworks.</p>

<h2>Support PackageReference in non .NET Core projects</h2>

<p>Non .NET Core Sdk style projects that use a PackageReference MSBuild item are now supported.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;PackageReference Include="Newtonsoft.Json"&gt;
  &lt;Version&gt;10.0.1&lt;/Version&gt;
&lt;/PackageReference&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>In Visual Studio for Mac 7.0 the Solution
window would not show any packages for the project, would not allow
the packages to be restored, and would create a packages.config file when installing
a NuGet package even though the project was using PackageReferences.</p>

<p>Now if the project has a PackageReference the Packages folder
shows the installed packages and can be used to update or install
NuGet packages which will also create PackageReference MSBuild items.</p>

<p>If the project has no PackageReferences then by default a
packages.config file will be created when a NuGet package is installed.</p>

<p>Currently it is not possible to opt-in to using PackageReferences by default.
So the project file will need to be edited in the text editor to include at
least one PackageReference before the default behaviour of using a packages.config
file is overridden.</p>

<h2>Enable file template when a NuGet package is installed</h2>

<p>A file template can now specify that it should be enabled if the project
has a specific reference or has a specific NuGet package installed.
Previously it was only possible to enable a file template based on the
references defined in the project file.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;HasPackageOrReference PackageId="Xamarin.Forms" Assembly="Xamarin.Forms" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Whilst a reference will work for projects that use a packages.config
file, if the project uses a project.json file or PackageReferences
then checking the references defined in the project would not find any matches and
the file template would not be enabled.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>Do not require description when creating a new NuGet package project</strong></p>

<p>When creating a NuGet package project or a multiplatform project the description
needed to be specified in the New Project dialog.</p>

<p>To simplify the project creation
process the package id is used as the description by default. As you type the
package id into the New Project dialog the description text
box will be updated. The description can be changed to be different
to the package id if required.</p>

<p><strong>Fix being unable to load NuGet Package Project created by Visual Studio on Windows</strong></p>

<p>Visual Studio on Windows creates a NuGet package project (.nuproj)
with no target framework version which resulted in 4.0 being used by
default in Visual Studio for Mac. This would cause the project to fail to
load in Visual Studio for Mac since it was checking for 4.5 or later.</p>

<p><strong>Fix no packages shown in Packages folder for NuGet Package Projects</strong></p>

<p>Opening a previously created NuGet package project (.nuproj) would show no
packages in the Packages folder.</p>

<p>The problem was that the PackageReference project item was defined by
both the NuGet addin and the Packaging addin. The NuGet addin&rsquo;s PackageReference
project item was used instead of the one defined by the Packaging addin so no
package references were found for the NuGet package project.</p>

<p><strong>Fix NuGet Package Project&rsquo;s MSBuild targets not being created</strong></p>

<p>If the NuGet package project&rsquo;s generated .nuget.targets or .nuget.props are missing
then these are now created on opening the solution if
automatic restore is enabled.</p>

<p><strong>Fix being unable to package .NET Standard projects</strong></p>

<p>A NuGet package project that referenced an Sdk style .NET Standard project
would fail to build the NuGet package. The build would fail with an error:</p>

<pre><code>Error: Project targets '.NETStandard,Version=v1.4'. It cannot be
referenced by a project that targets 'NuGet,Version=v1.0'
</code></pre>

<p>Updating to a more recent NuGet.Build.Packaging NuGet
package, such as version 0.1.276, fixes this problem.</p>

<p><strong>NuGet Package project treated as .NET Core project</strong></p>

<p>NuGet package projects (.nuproj) that use the NuGet.Build.Packaging
0.1.276 NuGet package define a TargetFramework property in an
imported MSBuild .props file. This was causing the project to
be treated as a .NET Core project by Visual Studio for Mac. This caused
the Dependencies folder to be displayed and the References folder
to be removed. Visual Studio for Mac now checks the project has the
Sdk attribute instead of looking at the MSBuild properties defined
by the project when determining the project type.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.NET Core Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/08/23/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-1/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-23T21:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/08/23/NetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>New Features</h2>

<ul>
<li> .NET Core 2.0 support</li>
<li> Target framework selection for new projects</li>
<li> New project templates</li>
<li> .NET Core Runtimes and SDKs displayed in About Dialog</li>
<li> Improved support for multi target framework projects</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.1</a> can be found in the <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/news/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes#release-date-august-14-2017---visual-studio-for-mac-7101297">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>.NET Core 2.0 Support</h2>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac 7.1 adds support for <a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/dotnet/2017/08/14/announcing-net-core-2-0/">.NET Core 2.0</a> and .NET Standard 2.0.</p>

<p>The .NET Core 2.0 SDK needs to be <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/net/download/core">installed</a> separately.</p>

<h2>Target Framework Selection for New Projects</h2>

<p>If a project template supports multiple target frameworks, and the corresponding framework is available, then the New Project dialog will allow the framework to be selected before the project is created.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/DotNetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-1/NewNetCoreProjectTargetFrameworkSelection.png" title="New .NET Core target framework selection" alt="New .NET Core target framework selection"></p>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac includes project templates for .NET Core 1.0, 1.1 and 2.0 as well as for .NET Standard versions 1.0 through to 2.0.</p>

<p>To be able to create projects that target .NET Core 2.0 or .NET Standard 2.0 the .NET Core 2.0 SDK needs to be installed.</p>

<h2>New Project Templates</h2>

<p>The following project templates have been added:</p>

<ul>
<li>ASP.NET Core Web App (Razor Pages)

<ul>
<li>Available if .NET Core 2.0 SDK is installed.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Class Library

<ul>
<li>Targets .NET Core instead of .NET Standard.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>MSTest</li>
</ul>


<p>Some project templates do not support all the target framework versions.
For example, the ASP.NET Core Web App (Razor Pages) only supports
.NET Core 2.0, so this template will only be displayed if .NET Core 2.0 SDK
is installed.</p>

<p>The F# project templates have some restrictions on what target frameworks
they support. The F# .NET Standard project templates do not
support selecting .NET Standard versions below 1.6. The F# Class Library project
only supports .NET Core 2.0.</p>

<h2>.NET Core Runtime and SDKs displayed in About Dialog</h2>

<p>The About dialog will now display the .NET Core runtimes and SDKs that are installed on
the local machine.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/DotNetCoreSupportInVisualStudioMac7-1/NetCoreInformationAboutDialog.png" title=".NET Core runtime and SDK information in About dialog" alt=".NET Core runtime and SDK information in About dialog"></p>

<h2>Improved Support for Multi Target Framework Projects</h2>

<p>SDK style projects that target multiple frameworks can now be opened in Visual Studio for
Mac 7.1 and will show source files as well as NuGet package dependencies.</p>

<p>The project will be treated as though it only has
one target framework which is the first one specified in the
TargetFrameworks property in the project file.</p>

<p>Please note that currently the support for multiple target frameworks is limited in
comparison with Visual Studio on Windows.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<p><strong>ASP.NET Core Web API project does not open API url on launching browser</strong></p>

<p>When an ASP.NET Core Web API project was run it would open a blank web
page in the browser instead of a page that showed the api values. Now when a new ASP.NET
Core Web API project is run the <code>http://localhost:&lt;port&gt;/api/values</code> url is launched in
the browser so the API values will be displayed.</p>

<p><strong>Unable to run or debug ASP.NET Core project with empty SDK directory</strong></p>

<p>If there was an empty directory inside the .NET Core SDK directory <code>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk</code> then it was
not possible to run or debug an ASP.NET Core web project</p>

<p>If the .NET Core SDK MSBuild files were not found in the SDK directory then the
project&rsquo;s OutputType was not read and would result in the project being treated
as a library project. This could also occur if only
the .NET Core runtime is installed.</p>

<p><strong>Shared project files shown for .NET Core project in Solution window</strong></p>

<p>When a .NET Core project referenced a shared assets project the files
from the shared project were incorrectly being displayed in the .NET Core project in
the Solution window.</p>

<p><strong>Fix generated code for resource files in .NET Core projects</strong></p>

<p>Adding a resx file to a .NET Core 1.x or .NET Standard 1.x project would result in
code being generated that could not be compiled.</p>

<p>Projects that target .NET Core App 1.0, 1.1, or .NET Standard below version 2.0
cannot compile code that uses <code>typeof(Resources).Assembly</code> which was
being generated by the ResXFileCodeGenerator. If these target frameworks
are used by the project then the code generated by Visual Studio for Mac
will now use <code>typeof(Resources).GetTypeInfo().Assembly</code> which is supported.</p>

<p>.NET Core 2.0 and .NET Standard 2.0 do not need to use GetTypeInfo so the
code generated for these frameworks has not been changed.</p>

<p><strong>Fix new resource file not added as Update item in Sdk projects</strong></p>

<p>Adding a new resource file to a .NET Core project would add the
.resx file and the .Designer.cs file as Include items instead of an
Update items.</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ItemGroup&gt;
  &lt;EmbeddedResource Include="Resources.resx"&gt;
    &lt;Generator&gt;ResXFileCodeGenerator&lt;/Generator&gt;
    &lt;LastGenOutput&gt;Resources.Designer.cs&lt;/LastGenOutput&gt;
  &lt;/EmbeddedResource&gt;
&lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
&lt;ItemGroup&gt;
  &lt;Compile Include="Resources.Designer.cs"&gt;
    &lt;DependentUpon&gt;Resources.resx&lt;/DependentUpon&gt;
  &lt;/Compile&gt;
&lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This then caused the build to fail since these files are already included by
the .NET Core SDK.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Configuring Open With in Visual Studio for Mac 7.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/08/06/ConfiguringOpenWithInVisualStudioMac7-0/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-06T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/08/06/ConfiguringOpenWithInVisualStudioMac7-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Visual Studio on Windows can be <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hy2sthf1.aspx">configured to use a different editor to open a file</a>. With Visual Studio for Mac, whilst you can open a file with a selection of editors and applications, it is not currently possible to change the default editor or add a custom application.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-open-with-addin">Open With addin</a> provides an Open With dialog that allows you to change the default editor or application used to open a file in a similar way to how this is done in Visual Studio on Windows.</p>

<h2>Features</h2>

<ul>
<li>Supports changing the default editor used to open a file.</li>
<li>Supports adding a custom application to open a file.</li>
<li>Editor configuration is saved and will be available on restarting Visual Studio for Mac.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Supports</h2>

<ul>
<li>Visual Studio Mac 7.0 or later.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Configuring the Default Editor or Application</h2>

<p>To configure the application or editor used to open file you can right click the file in the Solution window and select Open With &ndash; Preferences&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ConfiguringOpenWithInVisualStudioMac7-0/OpenWithPreferencesMenu.png" title="Open With - Preferences context menu" alt="Open With - Preferences context menu"></p>

<p>This will open the Open With dialog.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ConfiguringOpenWithInVisualStudioMac7-0/OpenWithDialog.png" title="Open With dialog" alt="Open With dialog"></p>

<p>The editors and applications that support opening the file are displayed. The default application is indicated by having (Default) next to its name.</p>

<p>To change the default application or editor used to open the file select it and then click the Set as Default button. Click OK to close the dialog and save the configuration.</p>

<p>If a file is currently open then it will need to be closed before it is opened in the new default editor or application.</p>

<h2>Adding a Custom Application</h2>

<p>A custom application can be added to the list of applications shown in the Open With menu. First open the Open With dialog by selecting Open With &ndash; Preferences. Then click the Add button to open the Add Application dialog.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/ConfiguringOpenWithInVisualStudioMac7-0/AddApplicationDialog.png" title="Add Application dialog" alt="Add Application dialog"></p>

<p>The Browse button can be used to find an application.</p>

<p>The Friendly Name is the name that will be displayed in the Open With menu for the custom application.</p>

<p>Arguments cannot be specified if a Mac application (.app) is used. However if the application is not a Mac application, for example, it is a C# program, then arguments can be passed. To pass the filename to the program you can use {0} in the Arguments text box. This placeholder will be expanded to be the full filename path when the program is run.</p>

<h2>Removing a Custom Application</h2>

<p>To remove a custom application for a file first open the Open With dialog by selecting Open With &ndash; Preferences. Select the application you want to remove. Then click the Remove button.</p>

<p>The Remove button is only enabled for custom applications that you have added. The built-in editors and applications cannot be removed.</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>The Open With addin is available to download from <a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-open-with-addin/releases/download/0.1/MonoDevelop.OpenWith_0.1.mpack">GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>To install the addin open the Extensions Manager by selecting Extensions&hellip; from the main menu. Click the Install from file button. Select the .mpack file and then click the Open button.</p>

<p>The addin is also in the Extensions Manager from the
<a href="http://addins.monodevelop.com/Project/Index/306">Visual Studio Extension Repository (Beta channel)</a>.</p>

<h2>Source Code</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mrward/monodevelop-open-with-addin">Open With addin for Visual Studio for Mac</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NuGet Support in Visual Studio for Mac 7.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/06/04/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-0/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-04T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2017/06/04/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>New Features</h2>

<ul>
<li> .NET Core support</li>
<li> NuGet 4.0 support</li>
</ul>


<p>More information on all the new features and changes in <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/vs/visual-studio-mac/">Visual Studio for Mac 7.0</a> can be found in the <a href="https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/news/releasenotes/vs2017-mac-relnotes">release notes</a>.</p>

<h2>.NET Core Support</h2>

<p>.NET Core projects do not show a Packages folder in the Solution window. Instead the NuGet packages are displayed in a NuGet folder, which is inside a Dependencies folder.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-0/NetCoreProjectJsonNetPackageInSolutionWindow.png" title="Newtonsoft.Json NuGet package in Solution window - .NET Core project" alt="Newtonsoft.Json NuGet package in Solution window - .NET Core project"></p>

<p>The version of the NuGet package is displayed directly in the Solution window. For other project types you need to right click the package to see the version.</p>

<p>If the NuGet package depends on other packages then these can be seen by clicking on the arrow to expand the dependencies.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-0/NetCoreProjectJsonNetPackageExpandedInSolutionWindow.png" title="Newtonsoft.Json NuGet package expanded in Solution window - .NET Core project" alt="Newtonsoft.Json NuGet package expanded in Solution window - .NET Core project"></p>

<h3>Restoring Packages</h3>

<p>NuGet packages will be restored automatically on opening a .NET Core project. This can be disabled in preferences by unchecking <strong>Automatically restore packages when opening a solution</strong> in the NuGet &ndash; General section.</p>

<p>You can manually restore NuGet packages for .NET Core projects by:</p>

<ul>
<li>Right clicking the Dependencies folder and selecting Restore.</li>
<li>Right clicking the NuGet folder and selecting Restore.</li>
<li>Selecting Restore NuGet Packages from the Project menu.</li>
</ul>


<p>Selecting Restore NuGet Packages from the Project menu will restore packages for the project or the solution depending on what is currently selected in the Solution window.</p>

<p>Restoring NuGet packages for a .NET Core project works differently compared with a project that uses a packages.config file. The NuGet packages themselves will be downloaded into the NuGet package cache folder ~/.nuget/packages if they do not exist, as before, but the NuGet packages will not be copied into a packages directory inside the solution&rsquo;s directory. The project file will not contain have any Reference items added when a NuGet package is installed.</p>

<p>When a NuGet restore is run for a .NET Core project three files in the obj directory are created.</p>

<ul>
<li>project.assets.json</li>
<li>ProjectName.csproj.nuget.g.props</li>
<li>ProjectName.csproj.nuget.g.targets</li>
</ul>


<p>The project.assets.json file contains the dependencies for your project.</p>

<p>The nuget.g.props and nuget.g.targets files will contain any MSBuild imports that your NuGet package requires and they also define some properties, such as the path to the NuGet package cache on your machine.</p>

<p>These three files are used when building your project to resolve the assemblies to be referenced now that they are no longer explicitly stored in your project file.</p>

<h3>Updating Packages</h3>

<p>NuGet packages can be updated by:</p>

<ul>
<li>Right clicking the package inside the NuGet folder and selecting Update.</li>
<li>Right clicking the NuGet folder and selecting Update.</li>
<li>Right clicking the Dependencies folder and selecting Update.</li>
<li>Selecting Update NuGet Packages from the Project menu.</li>
</ul>


<p>Selecting Update NuGet Packages from the Project menu will update all packages in the project or in the solution depending on what is currently selected in the Solution window.</p>

<h3>Removing Multiple NuGet Packages in One Step</h3>

<p>You can remove multiple NuGet packages in one step from a .NET Core project by selecting the packages in the Solution window, right clicking and selecting Remove.</p>

<p><img src="http://lastexitcode.com/images/blog/NuGetSupportInVisualStudioMac7-0/NetCoreProjectRemoveMultipleNuGetPackagesInSolutionWindow.png" title="Removing multiple NuGet packages in Solution window - .NET Core project" alt="Removing multiple NuGet packages in Solution window - .NET Core project"></p>

<p>Projects that use a packages.config file do not support removing multiple NuGet packages in one step.</p>

<h3>Installing NuGet Packages</h3>

<p>NuGet packages are installed by using the Add Packages dialog in the same way as with other project types. To open the Add Packages dialog for a .NET Core project:</p>

<ul>
<li>Right click the NuGet folder and select Add Packages&hellip;</li>
<li>Right click the Dependencies folder and select Add Packages&hellip;</li>
<li>Right click the project and select Add &ndash; Add NuGet Packages&hellip;</li>
<li>From the Project menu select Add NuGet Packages&hellip;</li>
</ul>


<p>When the first NuGet package is installed into a .NET Core project a packages.config file will not be created. Instead the NuGet package will be added as a <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/consume-packages/package-references-in-project-files">PackageReference</a> that is saved in the project file.</p>

<h3>Package Reference</h3>

<p>.NET Core projects do not use a packages.config file to record their NuGet dependencies. Instead the .NET Core project file will contain a <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/consume-packages/package-references-in-project-files">PackageReference</a> after the NuGet package is installed into the project.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;Project Sdk="Microsoft.NET.Sdk"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;PropertyGroup&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;OutputType&gt;Exe&lt;/OutputType&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;TargetFramework&gt;netcoreapp1.1&lt;/TargetFramework&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;/PropertyGroup&gt;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;ItemGroup&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;PackageReference Include="Newtonsoft.Json" Version="10.0.2" /&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;/ItemGroup&gt;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/Project&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Please note that Visual Studio for Mac currently only supports package references with the new SDK style projects which are used by .NET Core. If you use package references in other project types then the Solution window will not show the packages and a packages.config file will be created if you install a NuGet package.</p>

<h3>Updated Packages Available</h3>

<p>For other project types the Solution window will check for updated packages and show this information in the Packages folder. This is not currently supported with .NET Core projects.</p>

<h2>NuGet 4.0 Support</h2>

<p>Visual Studio for Mac now includes <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/release-notes/nuget-4.0-rtm">NuGet 4.0</a>.</p>

<p>More information on the new features provided by NuGet 4.&ndash; can be found in the <a href="http://blog.nuget.org/20170308/Announcing-NuGet-4.0-RTM.html">Announcing NuGet 4.0 RTM blog post</a> and the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/nuget/release-notes/nuget-4.0-rtm">NuGet 4.0 release notes</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
