<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: typescript | Matt Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/categories/typescript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-02T14:29:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://lastexitcode.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TypeScript Addin 0.6 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2015/08/09/TypeScriptAddin0-6Released/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-09T15:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2015/08/09/TypeScriptAddin0-6Released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new version of the TypeScript addin for Xamarin Studio and MonoDevelop has been released. The addin is available from <a href="http://addins.monodevelop.com/">MonoDevelop&rsquo;s Add-in Repository</a> in the alpha channel. More details on how to install the addin can be found in the <a href="/blog/2015/04/01/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/">TypeScript support in Xamarin Studio post</a>.</p>

<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li>Updated to support <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/typescript/archive/2015/07/20/announcing-typescript-1-5.aspx">TypeScript 1.5</a>.</li>
<li>Linux 32 bit and 64 bit are now supported with a single addin. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/chrisber">Christian Bernasko</a>.</li>
<li>Allow UMD and System modules to be selected in project options.</li>
</ul>


<p>The separate TypeScript Linux 32 bit addin is now deprecated since the TypeScript addin can now be used on 32 bit and 64 bit versions of Linux.</p>

<h2>Bug Fixes</h2>

<ul>
<li>TypeScript language service host not updated when the project options are changed</li>
</ul>


<p>For example, switching from ES3 to ES6 in the project options could cause the code completion to be incorrect since the language service host compiler settings were not being updated.</p>

<ul>
<li>TypeScript options shown when viewing solution options</li>
</ul>


<p>The TypeScript options are now only available when the project options are selected.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TypeScript Support in Xamarin Studio]]></title>
    <link href="http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2015/04/01/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-01T21:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lastexitcode.com/blog/2015/04/01/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Xamarin Studio and MonoDevelop now have support for <a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/">TypeScript</a> on Linux, Mac and Windows with an alpha release of the <a href="https://github.com/mrward/typescript-addin">TypeScript Addin</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/EditingTypeScriptInTextEditor.png" title="&lsquo;Editing TypeScript in Xamarin Studio on the Mac&rsquo; &lsquo;Editing TypeScript in Xamarin Studio on the Mac&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The TypeScript addin uses <a href="http://v8dotnet.codeplex.com">V8.NET</a> which is a library that allows a .NET application to host <a href="https://code.google.com/p/v8/">Google&rsquo;s V8 JavaScript engine</a> and have JavaScript interact with .NET objects in the host application.</p>

<p>The ability to support Windows, Mac and Linux would not have been possible without the work done by <a href="http://jameswilkins.net">James Wilkins</a> and <a href="https://github.com/chrisber">Christian Bernasko</a>. <a href="http://jameswilkins.net">James Wilkins</a> created the <a href="http://v8dotnet.codeplex.com">V8.NET</a> library and when it was first released it supported only Windows. <a href="https://github.com/chrisber">Christian Bernasko</a> then took V8.NET and modified it to make it work with Mono on Linux and the Mac. The TypeScript addin is using V8.NET binaries built by Christian from his port of <a href="https://github.com/chrisber/v8dotnet/tree/development-mono">V8.NET</a>.</p>

<p>Please note that this is an alpha release and because V8.NET uses a native library it can cause Xamarin Studio or MonoDevelop to terminate if a bug is encountered.</p>

<h2>Features</h2>

<ul>
<li>TypeScript compilation on save or build.</li>
<li>Code completion.</li>
<li>Find references.</li>
<li>Rename refactoring.</li>
<li>Go to declaration.</li>
<li>Errors highlighted as you type.</li>
<li>Code folding.</li>
</ul>


<p>The addin supports:</p>

<ul>
<li>Xamarin Studio MonoDevelop 5 and above.</li>
<li>TypeScript 1.4</li>
<li>Linux, Mac and Windows.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Installing the addin</h2>

<p>The addin is currently available from <a href="http://addins.monodevelop.com/">MonoDevelop&rsquo;s Add-in Repository</a> in the alpha channel. By default the alpha repository is not enabled so you will have to enable it before you can find and install the addin.</p>

<p>In Xamarin Studio open the Add-in Manager and select the Gallery tab. Click the repository drop down and if <strong>Xamarin Studio Add-in Repository (Alpha Channel)</strong> is not displayed then click <strong>Manage Repositories&hellip;</strong>. In the window that opens tick the check box next to <strong>Xamarin Studio Add-in Repository (Alpha Channel)</strong> and then click the Close button.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/AddingAlphaChannelAddins.png" title="&lsquo;Enabling alpha channel addins&rsquo; &lsquo;Enabling alpha channel addins&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Back in the Add-in Manager dialog click the Refresh button to update the list of addins. Use the search text box in the top right hand corner of the dialog to search for the addin by typing in <strong>TypeScript</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/AddinManagerTypeScriptAddin.png" title="&lsquo;TypeScript addin selected in Addin Manager dialog&rsquo; &lsquo;TypeScript addin selected in Addin Manager dialog&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Select the TypeScript addin and then click the <strong>Install&hellip;</strong> button.</p>

<p>Note that if you are using Linux 32 bit then you should install the <strong>TypeScript Linux 32 bit</strong> addin. The other <strong>TypeScript</strong> addin listed supports Linux 64 bit. Hopefully in the future it will be possible to support both Linux 32 bit and 64 bit using the same addin.</p>

<h2>Getting Started</h2>

<p>Now that the TypeScript addin is installed let us create a TypeScript file.</p>

<p>To add a TypeScript file open the New File dialog, select the <strong>Web</strong> category and select <strong>Empty TypeScript</strong> file.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/NewFileDialogNewTypeScriptFile.png" title="&lsquo;New File Dialog &ndash; New TypeScript File&rsquo; &lsquo;New File Dialog &ndash; New TypeScript File&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Give the file a name and click the New button.</p>

<p>Note that currently the TypeScript file needs to be included in a project. Standalone TypeScript project files are not supported. TypeScript files can be added to any .NET project.</p>

<h2>Code Completion</h2>

<p>When editing the TypeScript code you will have code completion when you press the dot character.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/TypeScriptCodeCompletion.png" title="&lsquo;TypeScript dot code completion&rsquo; &lsquo;TypeScript dot code completion&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Code completion also works when you type the opening bracket of a function.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/TypeScriptMethodCompletion.png" title="&lsquo;TypeScript method completion&rsquo; &lsquo;TypeScript method completion&rsquo;" ></p>

<h2>Go to Declaration</h2>

<p>The text editor&rsquo;s right click menu has three TypeScript menus: Go to Declaration, Find References and Rename.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/TypeScriptTextEditorContextMenu.png" title="&lsquo;Text editor context menu with TypeScript menu options&rsquo; &lsquo;Text editor context menu with TypeScript menu options&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The Go To Declaration menu option will open the corresponding definition in the text editor.</p>

<h2>Find References</h2>

<p>Find References will show the references in the Search Results window.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/TypeScriptReferencesInSearchResults.png" title="&lsquo;TypeScript references shown in Search Results window&rsquo; &lsquo;TypeScript references shown in Search Results window&rsquo;" ></p>

<h2>Rename</h2>

<p>Selecting the Rename menu option in the text editor will open the Rename dialog where you can type in a new name and click OK to have it updated.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/TypeScriptRenameDialog.png" title="&lsquo;TypeScript rename dialog&rsquo; &lsquo;TypeScript rename dialog&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Note that currently on Linux the Rename dialog will only be displayed if the keyboard shortcut F2 is used. Selecting the context menu will not show the Rename dialog on Linux but will work on Windows and on the Mac.</p>

<h2>Error Highlighting</h2>

<p>Errors in your TypeScript code will be highlighted as you are typing in the text editor.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/TypeScriptErrorsHighlightedInTextEditor.png" title="&lsquo;TypeScript errors highlighted in text editor&rsquo; &lsquo;TypeScript errors highlighted in text editor&rsquo;" ></p>

<h2>Code Folding</h2>

<p>Code folding is supported for TypeScript classes, modules and interfaces.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/TypeScriptCodeFolding.png" title="&lsquo;TypeScript code folding&rsquo; &lsquo;TypeScript code folding&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Code folding by default is disabled. To enable code folding open the Preferences dialog and in the Text Editor section select the General category, then tick the <strong>Enable code folding</strong> check box.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/PreferencesEnableCodeFolding.png" title="&lsquo;Preferences &ndash; Enabling code folding&rsquo; &lsquo;Preferences &ndash; Enabling code folding&rsquo;" ></p>

<h2>Compiling to JavaScript</h2>

<p>By default the TypeScript files will be compiled to JavaScript when the project is compiled.</p>

<p>There are more compiler options available in the project options in the Build &ndash; TypeScript category.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blog/TypeScriptSupportInXamarinStudio/TypeScriptCompilerOptions.png" title="&lsquo;TypeScript compiler options for the project&rsquo; &lsquo;TypeScript compiler options for the project&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>On this page you can change when the compiler is run and what options are passed to the compiler when generating JavaScript code.</p>

<p>If an <strong>Output file</strong> is specified then all the TypeScript files will be compiled into a single JavaScript file. If an <strong>Output directory</strong> is specified then the JavaScript files will be generated in that directory instead of next to the TypeScript files.</p>

<p>That is the end of our quick look at TypeScript support in Xamarin Studio and MonoDevelop.</p>

<h2>Source Code</h2>

<p>The source code for the addin and for the V8.NET engine that works on Mono are available on GitHub.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="ttps://github.com/mrward/typescript-addin/tree/monodevelop-v8-dotnet">TypeScript addin source code</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/chrisber/v8dotnet/tree/development-mono">V8.NET source code</a>.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
